<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of advice to a young lady being motives and directions to establish her in the Protestant religion / written by a person of honour.</title>
            <author>Person of honour.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25874</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11634400</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199118</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240875604</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1567</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11634400</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25874)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199118)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 3:46d)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of advice to a young lady being motives and directions to establish her in the Protestant religion / written by a person of honour.</title>
                  <author>Person of honour.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Richard Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata (one item): p. 48.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Conversion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199118:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER OF ADVICE To A <hi>Young Lady,</hi> BEING <hi>Motives</hi> and <hi>Directions</hi> To Establish Her In the Protestant Religion.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN <hi>By a Person of Honour,</hi> AND <hi>Made Publick for the Ʋse of that Sex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Baldwin,</hi> 1688.</p>
            <p>Price Three Pence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:199118:2"/>
            <p>Licensed,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> the 7th. 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:199118:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Letter of Advice,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Know the law of Custom has made it not only an <hi>usual favour,</hi> but an <hi>expected duty,</hi> to complement at least, if not flatter, such Women as Men write to, especially the Great Ladies, who think none <hi>write well,</hi> that do not <hi>praise them much,</hi> and those <hi>write best,</hi> who <hi>extol them most:</hi> high Praises be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like good Poetry, Musick in words, the sound of which may be <hi>agreable,</hi> but truly to <hi>deserve</hi> them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires such a <hi>Gygantick</hi> size of <hi>merit,</hi> as is very unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the slender-wasted <hi>Vertues</hi> of most La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, who are over-eager to <hi>receive</hi> Praises, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>careless in <hi>meriting</hi> any: and the grand reason is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they know they usually have them without it; and that <hi>Custome</hi> must give it, though <hi>Reason</hi> cannot. So obliging is the common courtesie of <hi>England</hi> to Ladies, that it allows them to pretend to all <hi>praises</hi> as their <hi>due,</hi> though few deserve any as their <hi>right.</hi> In a word, our <hi>English</hi> Ladies must have their <hi>Characters</hi> writ, just as the <hi>Dutch</hi> Madams will have their Pictures drawn, that is, very handsom, though they themselves be never so ugly.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Madam,</hi> for your part, I know your <hi>perfections</hi> so abundantly, and my own <hi>heart</hi> so truly, as I must beg the Law of <hi>Custome</hi> pardon here; it being beyond my pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to flatter or complement, since I can neither over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praise your high <hi>merit,</hi> or outspeak the real love, and true esteem, I have both for you and them; so that knowing all manner of <hi>praises</hi> to be justly due to your <hi>merits,</hi> I find I cannot here make you a present of any, without doing you an injury, by intitling you to those praises by <hi>gift,</hi> which all know are your own by <hi>right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For truly, <hi>Madam,</hi> the whole progress of your actions have still been so highly <hi>vertuous,</hi> and religiously strict, and ever believed and proclaimed such, that though your <hi>Beauty</hi> might make bad Men <hi>wish</hi> you ill, yet your <hi>Vertues</hi> hinder the worst from daring to <hi>think</hi> you so:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199118:3"/> for if they did, their own hearts must at the same time condemn their own thoughts, and declare your innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; like <hi>Pilate,</hi> who with the same breath he condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our Saviour, said, <hi>he found no fault in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, <hi>Madam,</hi> tho your vertuous life is so transpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly excellent, yet for all that, you ought to look on your unsoil'd Reputation as no small blessing of preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in these scandalous times, where so few handsom Ladies escape censure, and so many deserve it: for now the extravagancies of <hi>Romance-Amours</hi> are not only daily <hi>read,</hi> but almost hourly <hi>practised;</hi> and <hi>Women act</hi> more than <hi>Romances can write;</hi> whilst the sober Rules of <hi>Vertue,</hi> and pious Duties of <hi>Religion,</hi> are seldom thought on, and most ralely practised; our Youth being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally grown such fond friends of Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Books, as they are become meer <hi>strangers</hi> to our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s <hi>Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel;</hi> they living as if they were <hi>all bodies,</hi> and had <hi>no souls,</hi> or had them but to <hi>lose,</hi> turning <hi>Religion</hi> into <hi>Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery,</hi> and <hi>Gospel</hi> into <hi>Romances:</hi> for thus in short they mangle <hi>Scripture,</hi> that part which is chiefly <hi>Historical,</hi> that is their meer <hi>Gospel</hi>-part; and that which is the <hi>Gospel</hi>-part, is their meer <hi>Historical</hi>-part; and because they cannot <hi>bring the Gospel</hi> to prove their <hi>Atheistical reasons,</hi> pretend to prove by <hi>Reason,</hi> that there is <hi>no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel:</hi> and if some of them now and then look over a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they only <hi>pass through</hi> it, as a Spie doth an <hi>Enemies Country,</hi> with a <hi>mischievous design;</hi> and if they can but find in Scripture a <hi>seeming Contradiction,</hi> that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently bring on the Stage, as they do <hi>Fools</hi> in <hi>Plays,</hi> to <hi>railly</hi> with, and make <hi>sport</hi> at: so great a <hi>Jest</hi> our <hi>Young Sparks</hi> now make of their <hi>Salvation,</hi> as to be <hi>pleas'd</hi> in the meer <hi>displeasing God;</hi> without considering, 'tis not onely <hi>Atheistical madness,</hi> but <hi>Devillish folly,</hi> to make that their <hi>Jest,</hi> which they may be <hi>damn'd for in earnest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus our Youth throw away their <hi>Souls;</hi> and for their <hi>Time,</hi> they care not how they spend it, <hi>(always provided it be not religiously)</hi> and therefore they wast it most in the company of <hi>vain Women;</hi> and are so eager and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in their <hi>pursuit,</hi> and so constant in their <hi>service,</hi> as if they fancied God was <hi>mistaken,</hi> and intended creating
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199118:3"/>
               <hi>man for the woman,</hi> rather than <hi>the woman for the man.</hi> But though all know God made the <hi>Woman for the Man,</hi> yet what Critick can tell us whether our <hi>New Mode</hi> has made the <hi>Gallant for the Mistress,</hi> or the <hi>Mistress for the Gallant?</hi> But of this we are all sure, They are so plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully made for <hi>one another,</hi> that the Eastern Country-Laws allow not with more freedom <hi>plurality of Wives,</hi> than our new English Customs admit <hi>plurality of Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tresses.</hi> Nay, I may yet venture to say more, That the <hi>Liberty</hi> of our men <hi>exceeds</hi> theirs: for they are permitted no more <hi>Wives</hi> than they can well <hi>keep,</hi> but ours allow themselves as many <hi>Mistresses</hi> as they can any way <hi>get.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For indeed, the Names of <hi>Tom and Bess</hi> are hardly more familiar here, than those of <hi>Gallant and Mistress;</hi> and are so far from being esteemed Names of <hi>discredit,</hi> that many of our <hi>Mode-Ladies</hi> look on their <hi>Gallants</hi> as <hi>Beauty-marks,</hi> rather than <hi>stains</hi> of Reputation. And for all they cannot but know, that the <hi>infection of Gallants</hi> is as bad an Enemy to <hi>Credit,</hi> as the <hi>Small-pox</hi> to <hi>Beauty,</hi> a common <hi>ruiner</hi> of it: And though <hi>Womens Gallants</hi> are in plain <hi>English</hi> no better than the <hi>publick Execution<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of their <hi>reputations;</hi> and indeed no <hi>woman</hi> will allow them, but such as are <hi>willingly condem'd to suffer</hi> (and <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> that slight <hi>reputation</hi> are seldom fond of <hi>Chastity</hi>) Yet these <hi>abusers of love,</hi> and <hi>murderers of fame,</hi> by their <hi>fair words</hi> and <hi>base arts,</hi> have so insinuated themselves into their favour, as the <hi>women</hi> now forsooth, call their <hi>Gallants</hi> their <hi>Friends;</hi> and if common report may be credited they are indeed their <hi>bosom-ones;</hi> (and such <hi>women</hi> as value little what <hi>others say,</hi> seldom care much what they <hi>themselves do:</hi>) Custom having brought ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our <hi>women</hi> to that pass, as they now glory in the <hi>number</hi> of their <hi>Gallants,</hi> esteeming them rather so many <hi>Vouchers</hi> of their <hi>Beauty,</hi> than so many <hi>Robbers</hi> of their <hi>Honour;</hi> the so usual practice of this <hi>scandal,</hi> having taken away <hi>womens sense,</hi> that like blackness amongst the <hi>Aethiopians,</hi> its <hi>Commonness</hi> has removed its <hi>defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity:</hi> And there is now such a forward <hi>Love-spring</hi> in the Nurseries of our Young Ladies, as the very <hi>little-ones</hi> learn to spell <hi>Amour</hi> with their <hi>Fescue,</hi> and will pretend
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199118:4"/> to <hi>entertain</hi> their <hi>Young Gallants,</hi> in the dark walks of <hi>Love,</hi> and in the Labyrinth of its <hi>Intrigues,</hi> before they well know what the thing <hi>Love</hi> is, or the name of <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant</hi> means; and would have <hi>Servants</hi> come to them, before they come to the <hi>Teens,</hi> (the <hi>ripeness</hi> of their <hi>minds</hi> outrunning that of their <hi>bodies</hi>) and fancy <hi>men</hi> so mad as to believe, 'tis <hi>expectation</hi> makes a <hi>Blessing dear.</hi> But that dull <hi>Presbyterian way</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> is now quite out of Fashion, and the loves of our <hi>Young Gallants</hi> are grown as <hi>fickle,</hi> and meer <hi>skin-deep,</hi> as their Mistresses <hi>Fancies</hi> and <hi>Beauties;</hi> and <hi>Love-wounds</hi> that are but <hi>skin-deep,</hi> can never hurt the <hi>heart;</hi> and therefore though every day we hear of Hundreds of <hi>Gallants</hi> that are <hi>dying for Love</hi> in their <hi>Mistresses company,</hi> yet we cannot read of one these many <hi>Ages</hi> that <hi>dyed for love</hi> in the <hi>Weekly-Bills</hi> of Mortality; the <hi>obliging carriage</hi> of the Ladies of the times having made our <hi>Young Men</hi> so <hi>healthfully wise,</hi> so <hi>forwardly bold,</hi> or at least so <hi>impatiently hasty,</hi> as they expect now a-days to take <hi>Young Women,</hi> as great Armies do <hi>weak Towns,</hi> only by <hi>Summons,</hi> or <hi>Assaults;</hi> as not esteeming them <hi>worthy</hi> the time and trouble of a <hi>Love-siege,</hi> though their Mistresses were as yielding as <hi>Rome</hi> it self, which Writers say, was <hi>never besieged without being taken:</hi> that is, in short, they hold hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Women worth <hi>enjoying,</hi> but not <hi>wooing.</hi> And that makes our <hi>Young Men</hi> so eager and inconstant in their <hi>Amours,</hi> as really tis a very hard measuring-cast to tell whether your <hi>Young Gallants</hi> use now more art, or speed, in the <hi>getting</hi> or <hi>forgetting</hi> of their <hi>Mistresses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the best of it is, that the <hi>inconstancy</hi> of <hi>both Sexes</hi> are now so equally match'd, that I cannot write more of their <hi>Gallants</hi> inconstancies, than their <hi>Mistresses</hi> make good of their own: For they deal with their <hi>Gallants,</hi> as their <hi>Fashions;</hi> that which comes <hi>latest,</hi> is still <hi>lik'd best,</hi> and <hi>us'd most.</hi> In a word, the constancy and inconstancy of Young Men and Women, are just like <hi>water</hi> and <hi>ice,</hi> where one still <hi>makes</hi> the other; and their <hi>loves</hi> (Ice-like) never <hi>last long;</hi> and as soon as 'tis <hi>dissolv'd,</hi> turns immediately <hi>to the same</hi> it was before, without any <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration</hi> or <hi>prejudice:</hi> Nor can <hi>water</hi> be more apt and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:199118:4"/> ready by the coming of <hi>Frost</hi> to turn to <hi>Ice,</hi> than our Young Men and Womens hearts are apt and enclin'd to <hi>return to love,</hi> at the approach of <hi>fresh-fancied Beauty.</hi> And truly the inconstancy of our Young Men cannot be <hi>so great,</hi> nor their inclinations <hi>so ill,</hi> but the <hi>tongues</hi> of many of our Young Women are grown <hi>as bad:</hi> For now if a Young Maid be but cry'd up for <hi>handsom,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solves to continue <hi>vertuous,</hi> and therefore will not turn <hi>vain,</hi> and deserve <hi>censure,</hi> as much as the rest, they will be sure to speak her as <hi>bad</hi> as the <hi>worst;</hi> and if they cannot with <hi>justice</hi> wound her <hi>Vertue,</hi> they will attempt by ill <hi>arts</hi> to <hi>murder</hi> her <hi>Reputation, (Envy</hi> being the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of <hi>wicked invention</hi>) it being now a <hi>Mode-principle</hi> amongst most of our <hi>handsom Women,</hi> that no Woman that enjoys a large proportion of <hi>Beauty,</hi> but must, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an unavoidable appurtenance, carry with it a load of scandalous <hi>censures</hi> (a false Character of <hi>some,</hi> though too true a one of most) which occasions their not caring how unjustly they increase anothers <hi>burthen,</hi> in hope to lessen their own <hi>load;</hi> and by <hi>overstretching</hi> the miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of others greater than they should be, hope to <hi>shrink</hi> theirs less than really they are; vainly fancying, that <hi>spattering</hi> with dirt and reproach other Womens <hi>reputations,</hi> were a kind of <hi>wiping clean</hi> their own; which suits not at all with the mild and moderate rules of <hi>Vertue,</hi> which only allows Women to correct each others <hi>faults,</hi> by their <hi>good Examples,</hi> but not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease them by their <hi>bad censures.</hi> For, <hi>scandalous cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures,</hi> like <hi>Mushooms,</hi> grow <hi>without any root;</hi> so tender and mutable a thing is a <hi>handsom Womans good Name:</hi> there's no taking its <hi>true Elevation</hi> by any certain out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>measures,</hi> since it depends more on her Neighbours good or bad <hi>report,</hi> than on her vertuous or ill <hi>actions;</hi> and more on what <hi>they say,</hi> than what <hi>she does.</hi> And really such <hi>reports</hi> are usually so sophisticated with <hi>self-concerns,</hi> and so strongly byass'd by <hi>aversion</hi> or <hi>incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> as you may daily hear in common Discourse, both Men and Women turn <hi>Vertue into Vice,</hi> and <hi>Vice into Vertue;</hi> and so characterize <hi>Good</hi> Women to be <hi>bad,</hi> and <hi>bad</hi> Women to be <hi>good;</hi> speaking not as Women <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:199118:5"/> but as they <hi>fancy;</hi> and therefore it often happens, that many Women <hi>save their reputations,</hi> even by a speedy <hi>losing their chastity,</hi> whilst other Women <hi>lose their repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> in their very <hi>defence of it;</hi> that is, in short, more Women lose their <hi>reputation</hi> in admitting to be <hi>much courted</hi> (though that be all) than by being <hi>ill injoyn'd:</hi> And the reason is plain, Because the <hi>Courtship</hi> is <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> to all, but the <hi>injoyment</hi> is only <hi>private</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and 'tis more rational two <hi>concerned persons</hi> should keep their own counsel, than many <hi>unconcern'd</hi> should keep it for them; so that it cannot necessarily follow, that the <hi>roported reputation</hi> or disreputation of handsom Women must needs be the <hi>true issue</hi> of their <hi>merits,</hi> but often the <hi>by-blow</hi> of <hi>chance;</hi> and therefore <hi>common report</hi> can be no <hi>right rule</hi> to measure Womens <hi>reputations</hi> by: For many reports have much of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils nature</hi> in them, who is <hi>a lyar from the beginning.</hi> And indeed, if we but truly consider, we shall find Women general censure <hi>one another,</hi> not as they are <hi>really</hi> faulty, but as they <hi>appear,</hi> and are <hi>esteemed handsom;</hi> and therefore <hi>ugly Women</hi> have the priviledge of <hi>Popes,</hi> who <hi>cannot err,</hi> but may do <hi>what they will,</hi> and take what <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> they please; and <hi>handsom Women</hi> will be as far from censuring their <hi>actions,</hi> as <hi>Young Men</hi> from praising their <hi>persons:</hi> So that really in effect, we find most Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens <hi>censures</hi> are not proportionable to the <hi>ill</hi> others <hi>act,</hi> but rather suitable to the <hi>Beauty</hi> they <hi>possess;</hi> which by their leave is a way of <hi>judging,</hi> that's both <hi>iriational</hi> and <hi>uncharitable;</hi> since I am sure none can <hi>deny,</hi> but there are some <hi>unhandsom Women unchast;</hi> and some <hi>chast Women handsom:</hi> For <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> are not so declar'd enemies, but they sometimes meet; though I cannot deny, but that <hi>Vertue</hi> which in former Ages was esteemed one of the greatest <hi>adornments</hi> of the <hi>soul,</hi> is now so <hi>Eclipsed</hi> by the outward <hi>Beauty</hi> of the Body, as <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> (the true <hi>inward Beauty</hi>) cannot shine out: A <hi>good Soul</hi> being nothing now in comparison of a <hi>good face; Beauty</hi> being now the <hi>Great Empress</hi> that commands the whole World, and makes the Supremest of men become subjects to Her. And yet this so <hi>ador'd
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:199118:5"/> Beauty,</hi> (which all Women are so <hi>ambitious of,</hi> and all Men so <hi>court</hi>) has at best no <hi>intrinsick</hi> value in it, but just like <hi>riches,</hi> they <hi>enjoy most,</hi> that are contented <hi>with least;</hi> since 'tis not <hi>much,</hi> but <hi>enough,</hi> that's the <hi>true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure</hi> of satisfaction. But <hi>Madam,</hi> 'tis now more than time to beg your pardon; for I find I am stray'd both beyond the <hi>time,</hi> and beside the <hi>road</hi> of my design'd Discourse, which is not to present you a <hi>Character,</hi> or <hi>List</hi> of the <hi>fine Ladies,</hi> and <hi>Mode-vices</hi> of the times; they will require a much <hi>wittier Pen</hi> than I pretend to be Master of, and a <hi>larger Volume</hi> than I design to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with: but this <hi>Character</hi> which indeed merits <hi>Volumes of Praises,</hi> I am sure I can give <hi>you,</hi> without needing <hi>wit,</hi> or abusing of <hi>time;</hi> and if I could here cast up the sum total of all the <hi>vices</hi> that <hi>your Sex</hi> are eitheir <hi>guilty of,</hi> or <hi>scandaliz'd with,</hi> (which I'le assure you are <hi>more than a few</hi>) their number might be <hi>tedious to read,</hi> but need not be <hi>disagreeable for you to bear,</hi> since by nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all those faults they are <hi>infected with,</hi> I should but tell all those you are <hi>free from.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, <hi>Madam,</hi> my design is now to remove my Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and change my Scene of Writing, as you have your place of Living; and to level my Discourse, not at the <hi>vices</hi> and <hi>pleasures</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> nor the <hi>pastimes</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> but at your Country-Neighbours, the Woods and Mountains of <hi>Macroome,</hi> which renders it a place much fitter to exercise <hi>your</hi> past-time, than satisfie your delight, were <hi>you</hi> of the humour of most <hi>Ladies;</hi> but all know <hi>you</hi> are not only an <hi>excellent Woman,</hi> but an <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary wife,</hi> I mean in <hi>Goodness,</hi> (for 'tis rare now to meet a <hi>wife</hi> that's not <hi>extraordinary</hi>) for <hi>you</hi> take as much satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the cares of well managing and improving <hi>your</hi> Estate, as most other <hi>Ladies</hi> delight, in the lavishing <hi>theirs;</hi> so that I can truly say, <hi>you</hi> have not only brought <hi>your Lord</hi> a large sum of <hi>money</hi> for <hi>your Portion,</hi> but a continued increase of <hi>Rent</hi> by <hi>your</hi> Industry.</p>
            <p>And I am sure, <hi>Madam,</hi> if you were now askt as the <hi>Philosopher</hi> was, <hi>Where was his home?</hi> you would answer now, as he did then, <hi>My home is still where my chief business is.</hi> So that now your chief Concerns and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199118:6"/> Family, (which is still the <hi>good Wives Treasure</hi> (being at <hi>Macroome,</hi> I must conclude <hi>your heart</hi> is there also.</p>
            <p>A place, where in lieu of <hi>London,</hi> crowds of good Company, and swarms of divertisements, you must pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to meet with, and do Penance to your self, <hi>among the Flocks of Priests and Fryars, against whose Popish insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations, and infectious perswasions,</hi> I here present you a small, but necessary <hi>Collection</hi> of Arguments to carry about you, as a <hi>Preservatitive</hi> in your own <hi>Religion,</hi> and an <hi>Antitode</hi> against <hi>theirs;</hi> and though I cannot pretend this <hi>pocket-Pistol</hi> is a sufficient <hi>Battering-piece,</hi> to beat down their <hi>infallible Church,</hi> yet I doubt not but it will at least be a sufficient <hi>Life-guard</hi> to defend you and your <hi>Chamber</hi> against their <hi>assaults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are most of them <hi>argumentative reasonings</hi> I pickt out of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> as one that <hi>reasons best, and satisfies me most,</hi> of any I ever read; and knowing you want a Collection of choice Flowers, <hi>I heartily wish</hi> that these I have gathered out of his <hi>Garden,</hi> and here sorted and made up to present you in a <hi>Nosegay,</hi> may serve you against the <hi>unpleasing savour</hi> of <hi>Popish Doctrine:</hi> And I wish they may not altogether degenerate from common <hi>nature</hi> of Flowers, which the Naturalist tells us, grow <hi>larger</hi> and <hi>better</hi> by being <hi>transplanted;</hi> so that I hope you will not find them the worse, nor like them the less, for being <hi>transplanted,</hi> but receive these Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments just as you do your Rents, without caring whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your <hi>Tenants</hi> have the Money out of their own <hi>bags,</hi> or borrow it, so you have it to supply your occasions.</p>
            <p>Truly, <hi>Madam,</hi> I have taken some pains, and spent much time in reading the Discourses of <hi>Papists against our Religion;</hi> and though I have consider'd their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without the least <hi>Byas,</hi> or <hi>antedated prejudice;</hi> yet I can give no better <hi>a character</hi> of them, than I do of ill Dealers, <hi>The more I have to do with them, the worse</hi> I <hi>like them:</hi> They savour much of Self-interest, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Church-Government,</hi> before <hi>Gospel-Obedience;</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness their holding <hi>Marriage</hi> a greater crime in a Priest, than <hi>Fornication:</hi> The one is but forbid by their <hi>Churches Law,</hi> which they all know is disputable, the latter by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199118:6"/> the Law of <hi>Christ,</hi> which they cannot but know, ought to be past all dispute.</p>
            <p>And truly, <hi>Madam,</hi> if you please to admit <hi>your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> to make but a short progress <hi>into the Popish Religion,</hi> you shall find much to create <hi>your wonder,</hi> but little to <hi>satisfie your reason or belief;</hi> for the Gospel of <hi>Christ</hi> is the Gospel of Truth, and therefore ought still to be pictur'd naked as <hi>Truth,</hi> without any Art of <hi>Roman</hi> Dresses, which are only obscure shadings of the true light of <hi>Scripture,</hi> by making dark <hi>Paraphrases</hi> on the plainest <hi>Gospel-Commands,</hi> which in all reason ought to be plain enough for the meanest <hi>capacity:</hi> For <hi>God</hi> forbid it should be otherwise; for the meanest <hi>Christian</hi> must be <hi>saved</hi> or <hi>damned,</hi> for keeping or not keeping them; and sure <hi>God's</hi> Justice will never send persons t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hell, for not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they could not understand was his Will they should do; that were such a cruelty, as if a man should torment his Servant for not doing his Errant, when he knew he did not understand his Message; yet the <hi>Papist</hi> must not take these plain <hi>Gospel-Commands</hi> as such, but as they are distill'd in the mysterious <hi>politick Lymbeck</hi> of the <hi>Popish interest:</hi> Indeed <hi>Mystery</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> is so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwoven in that Religion, that <hi>Papists</hi> must take what their Priest tells them, as Men do Wives, for better, for worse, and must marry their <hi>Faith</hi> to their Churches <hi>infallibility,</hi> which allows that only to be <hi>Gospel,</hi> which their Church says shall be, not what the <hi>Apostles</hi> write is so; for the Papists must obey the Pope, though no where commanded in the Gospel; but must not read the Gospel, though they are commanded there to do it.</p>
            <p>Nay, when once the Papist can but touch the small Needle of any ones reason with the great Loadstone of the Harmonious Doctrine of <hi>a necessary Obedience</hi> to their infallible Church, then they make such follow it, to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry point of the Compass, be it good, bad, or indifferent; and so they sail all their life, in a Trade-wind of <hi>ignorance and superstition,</hi> and must believe their Priests words before their own senses, in the plainest objects of them; as in the Miracle of <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> where you must have eyes and see not, and hands and feel not, but must
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199118:7"/> believe in a moment <hi>real Bread and Wine</hi> to be turned into <hi>perfect Flesh and Blood,</hi> though you cannot see the least <hi>change</hi> whatsoever: yet they are bound to believe their <hi>Priest,</hi> before their <hi>eyes, smell, tast;</hi> nor dare their Priest say, that the <hi>Consecrated Bread</hi> (which they esteem the real Body of Christ) will be less <hi>mouldy,</hi> or more uncertain of <hi>corruption</hi> after <hi>Consecration</hi> than before; and the jest of it is, that at the same time the Papists believe that Miracle, they also believe this Scripture, <hi>That God will not suffer his Holy One to see corruption.</hi> And tho for these and many other reasons, I cannot believe this <hi>Transubstantiation-Miracle;</hi> yet I cannot but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire this <hi>Miracle</hi> that belongs to <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> which is, how the Pope can bring so many, that have sense and reason to believe it.</p>
            <p>But I shall pass by their <hi>adoring</hi> this <hi>Sacrament,</hi> their <hi>praying</hi> to <hi>Saints,</hi> and a multitude of their <hi>superstitious observances</hi> never used in the <hi>Primative Church;</hi> &amp; shall only desire you, <hi>Madam,</hi> to observe in general, that the <hi>Papists</hi> follow the Gospel, just as they read <hi>Hebrew,</hi> that's back ward; for God plainly commands, that <hi>all should search the Scripture.</hi> And our Blessed Saviour ordered the <hi>Sacrament</hi> to be administred in <hi>both kinds,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> forbids publick Prayers in an <hi>unknown Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> but that which is most for <hi>Edification,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15, 16. But these plain positive commands do not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> from declaring, <hi>that unlearned men shall not read and search the Scriptures;</hi> but if we believe St. <hi>Paul</hi> before the <hi>Pope,</hi> we may read in the 17th of the <hi>Acts,</hi> 11. how he commended the noble <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> for searching the Scriptures; and therefore if <hi>sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Scriptures</hi> had not been not only lawful, but a commendable act, certainly St. <hi>Paul</hi> would never have commended them for so doing. So that the <hi>Popish Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> forbids the reading the Scriptures, under pretence that their Laity might not truly understand them. Next, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> allows only their Clergy (except free Princes, for they are excepters of Persons, though God is not) to receive the Communion but in <hi>one kind,</hi> tho our Saviour commands, <hi>that all drink of the Cup;</hi> and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:199118:7"/> the Papists cannot deny, but that the Communion was taken in <hi>both kinds</hi> in all Christian Churches for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a Thousand Years after Christ.</p>
            <p>And lastly, for the poor vulgar sort, they shall only hear their publick Prayers in an <hi>unknown Tongue,</hi> viz. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> which a Tenth part of them do not understand; and therefore how that can be most for Edification, let the <hi>Papists</hi> tell if they can; I am sure we cannot, nor do we believe they can, without the help of another <hi>Transubstantiation-Miracle,</hi> and making an <hi>unknown Language</hi> to most to be chang'd at the same time into a common <hi>known Language</hi> to all.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Madam,</hi> I shall humbly desire you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider in general, that tho the <hi>Papists do out-noise us</hi> (as shallow Rivers do still the deepest) with the high and mighty <hi>Rodomontades</hi> of their <hi>Churches Infallibility;</hi> yet such high Rants, without true proof, are but like School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boys paper-Kites, which soar high and lofty, but have nothing else worth taking notice of. They will have the confidence to tell you, that their Popish Church is the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, and only true Christian Church in the whole World: But the <hi>Protestants</hi> Answer to this their boasting, is, that all the Christian Churches in the whole World (besides the Popish Churches, tho more in number than they) declare quite contrary. They will ask you, <hi>where your Protestant Church was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> Luther; which was wittily answered by one; <hi>(where the Papist Church never was)</hi> in the Bible.</p>
            <p>The Papists do divert themselves very much at our stiling our King, <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> as we do, for their doing so: for we esteem our King Head only in his own Dominions, without the Popes title of infallible; and sure 'tis more rational that those of a Kingdom should allow their King to be <hi>Head of the Church</hi> in his own Kingdoms, than that a few Cardinals should make the <hi>Head of the Church</hi> over all Kingdoms. And for all their jeasting, I am sure we can shew (in sober ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest) Scripture-presidents for Kings being Heads of Churches in their own Dominions, which is more than the Papists can shew for their Pope, or his Churches
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:199118:8"/>
               <hi>infallibility:</hi> For sure they cannot object against it as new Doctrine (though Doctrine that's new is their greatest Trade) that the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the first Christian Emperors were Heads of the <hi>Jewish</hi> Churches, and in their own Dominions: And <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>That a Divine Sentence is in the lips of the King, and his mouth transgresseth not in Judgment:</hi> (which I am sure Popes have not, witness <hi>Liberius</hi>) and <hi>Solomon</hi> gives the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, because the Heart of the King is in the Hand of the Lord. If the Papists will pretend so much Scripture for their Pope, I shall only answer, 'Tis more than ever Protestants read, or the Apostles writ.</p>
            <p>The Papists will tell you with a great deal of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, though we say the Bible is the Religion of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, yet there is no Protestant Religion, or Church, mentioned in the whole Creed, which are the Articles of the Christian Faith: And they will tell you, that their Church is the Catholick Church; and to believe the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, was an Article of the Christian Faith from the <hi>very infancy</hi> of the Church in the beginning of the Apostles time. Now let the Papists tell us, if they bring this as an Argument against the Protestant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the Bible, or not; if not, what cause have they to name it, or what need have we to answer it? but if it be one, we make this reply; <hi>That the Roman Church is no more named in the Apostles Creed, than the Protestant Church is; for the Apostles Creed was made before the Roman Church was a Church;</hi> and this I am sure they cannot deny; so that since the Catholick Church wa<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> then in being, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church <hi>not</hi> in being, it must necessarily follow, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church cannot be the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church mentioned in the <hi>Apostles Creed</hi> and consequently is not the <hi>Mother-Church,</hi> as the Papist<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> would have her to be: Thus the Papists have so over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd this Argument to shoot at us, as it recoils and flyes in their <hi>own faces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of kin to this, is their grand <hi>Battering-piece</hi> of all, which so <hi>thunders</hi> in the ears of all <hi>Papists,</hi> and makes the <hi>Popes power</hi> so absolute, and the <hi>poor credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Papist</hi> so obedient, and that is the power given by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199118:8"/> our Saviour to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in the 16th of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the 18th Verse, <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and on this Rock I will build my Church, and give thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven; and whomsoever thou shalt bind on Earth, shall be bound in Heaven; and whomsoever thou shalt loose on Earth, shall be loosed in Heaven;</hi> and these words the Papists understand literally, that St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s person is the Rock that <hi>Christ</hi> builds his Church on; which cannot possibly be, by the <hi>verses</hi> just following: For there when our Saviour tells his Disciples <hi>of his going to</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>where he must suffer many things, and be killed, and raised again the Third day;</hi> Peter <hi>took him, and rebuke him, Be it far from thee, Lord, this shall not be unto thee:</hi> But our Saviour turned, and said unto <hi>Peter, Get thee behind me, Satan, thou art an offence to me, for thou savourest not the things that he of God, but those that be of men.</hi> By which words 'tis most clear and evident, that our Saviour did not mean <hi>Peters</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son could be the Rock of the Christian Church: For if <hi>Peter</hi>'s person had been that Rock meant, sure our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour would never have removed it behind him; and it would be not only irrational, but impious, to believe that Christ would build his Church on Satan, for so he calls St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s person; and it were as unreasonable to believe that the Rock of Christ's Church could be an offence to him, as St. <hi>Peter's</hi> person was; and as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable again as all this, that Christ's Church, the Foundation of all Christianity, should savour, not of the things that be of God, but those that are of Men, as <hi>Peter</hi>'s person did.</p>
            <p>Therefore if you but please to read the words of our Saviour carefully, you shall find they are most plain: for Verse 13th. <hi>When Jesus came into the Coast of</hi> Caesa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea, <hi>He ask'd his Disciples, Whom do men say that I am? and they said, Some say that thou art</hi> John <hi>the Baptist, some</hi> Elias, <hi>and others</hi> Jeremias, <hi>or one of the Prophets: but whom say ye that I am? and</hi> Simon Peter <hi>answered and said, Thou art Christ-the Son of the Living God: And I say also unto thee, that thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and upon this Rock,</hi> (not this person) <hi>I will build my Church; that is</hi> (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:199118:9"/> this Rock of Faith) <hi>that I am Christ the Son of the Living God, I build my Church, and the Gates of Hell shall not prevail against it.</hi> Now this must <hi>necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily</hi> relate to his <hi>faith,</hi> not his <hi>person;</hi> for the <hi>gates of Hell,</hi> that's the <hi>power of evil,</hi> did prevail against <hi>Peter</hi>'s person, or he had not <hi>deny'd</hi> and <hi>forsworn</hi> his Lord and Master again and again; and been afterwards proved <hi>blame-worthy</hi> by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>face,</hi> and indeed as <hi>blame-worthy</hi> as any of his <hi>Disciples.</hi> So that 'tis most plain, that <hi>Christ</hi>'s words (of making him the <hi>Rock</hi> of the <hi>Christian Church</hi>) related not to his <hi>person,</hi> but his <hi>faith</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi>'s being the <hi>Son of the Living God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the other part; whereas the Papists believe a particular <hi>favour</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> given by our Saviour to St. <hi>Peter;</hi> of the Keys of Heaven; that was given as much to the Eleven Disciples, as to him, as you may read in the 18th of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> and in the 20th of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Gospel, Vers. 23, 24. <hi>As my Father hath sent me, even so send I you: and when he had said this, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive ye the Holy Ghost: whosesoever sins ye remit, they are remitted unto them, and whosesoever sins ye retain, they are retained.</hi> So that you see this power is general to the Disciples, and not in particular to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> more than to <hi>any</hi> of the rest, as the Papists misbelieve.</p>
            <p>The Papists have many such Questions, which I am sure, <hi>Madam,</hi> you have neither the patience to read, nor I the time to write; but those that are most <hi>material</hi> of them, <hi>you</hi> will find I have here presented <hi>you,</hi> truly answer'd, by pure <hi>Scripture,</hi> clear <hi>reasons,</hi> plain <hi>arguments,</hi> and all in few words, fit for the weakest memory, or small<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est pocket, to carry about them: For true <hi>reason</hi> doth not consist in large <hi>Volumes,</hi> long <hi>Gowns,</hi> or gray <hi>Beards;</hi> for many live to One and twenty, without attaining to years of discretion; the degrees of Age being not still the measures of Wisdom: For the World will never be without old Fools and young Philosophers.</p>
            <p>And truly, <hi>Madam,</hi> for my part, I cannot so much as think of the Papists Religion without wonder, that so many rational men of them should rather fasten their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199118:9"/> faith of <hi>salvation</hi> on the pretended <hi>infallibility</hi> of their Church (which is deny'd by most Christians) than on the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> which is granted by all, to be the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>very</hi> Foundation of their Churches Foundation, as containing in it all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to our salvation. And we Protestants have at least this satisfaction and advantage, that not only the Papists, but all sorts of Christians that are in the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the whole World, meet and joyn with us in this center of Faith, <hi>That the Scriptures contain all things necessary to our salvation;</hi> which being a general grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Truth, I confess I admire how any Papist can make the least scruple, which is the safest Heavenly Guide, the <hi>Pope,</hi> or the <hi>Gospel.</hi> If there be any rational man so <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant</hi> as to put them in the same <hi>ballance,</hi> and to commit a <hi>rape</hi> upon his <hi>Reason,</hi> I shall only desire him to consider this plain Question. If he were to go a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in an unknown way, would he not think it more rational and safe to follow a certain true Guide, that all the Christians in the World declare is certainly able and ready to shew him the right way, than to follow a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Guide, which the greatest part of the Christians in the World assures him will lead him out of it. And this being the real difference between the Papist and Protestant in gross, concerning the Heavenly Guide, the Bible, and the Pope, I think I need now say no more, because so many have already said so much, and I am sure enough to satisfie any, except such, who will believe a crooked Rule is better to draw a straight line by, than a right one.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Madam,</hi> I shall only beg so much of your patience, as to let me tell you, that the plot and Heads of this following discourse, I have Extracted out of the worthy <hi>Collingworth.</hi> Before I begin the discourse it self, I know, in writing a Play, to have Rank'd the plot in the Front of it, and to make the whole design of the Prologue to be the Key to uncipher the plot of the Play, (though anciently in use) had been now, not only out of fashion, but beside reason: For the design of Plays aiming chiefly to please the senses, they ought
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199118:10"/> to be compounded and mixt with hopes and fears, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties and uncertainties, expectations and delays of the event of the plot; which being all so interwoven together, creates the agreeableness of the Play; for when once the whole plot is discovered, the pleasure of the Play is ended; like Hare-Hunting, the sport lies not in presently taking the Hare, but in following him, in all his Rings and Doubles. And those that love Plays, and such Huntings, resemble jealous men, who eagerly pursue what they apprehend to overtake; or as old Age, which we all pray to attain, but fear to approach.</p>
            <p>But now I come to soar my discourse to a much higher pitch, and a more Elevated Subject, and to treat of the most noble part of man, the Soul; and of true Religion the only way to Heavenly felicity: For <hi>without Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, no man shall see the Lord.</hi> We must therefore now, <hi>Madam,</hi> change the Scene of sense for a spiritual one, and climb where earthly nature can never follow us, to the pure and high Region of Heaven; which will inform us that the earlier discovering our plot of attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heaven, will but better the play; and the more speed, the better success: For the joys of Heaven are everlasting, and admit of no increase or diminution: not like the divertisements of Stage-plays, or Hunting, or any earthly delights, which cannot last but for a sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and decay in our very injoying them, and must soon leave us, or we them: But Heavenly thoughts, the more and longer we practice them, the better we shall like them; Heavenly joys so far exceeding all we can here leave, as they are all we can ever aspire to have: This we all know, but few of us practice; and we all love God, but few love to keep his Commandments.</p>
            <p>I shall therefore now, <hi>Madam,</hi> tell you, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue to my insuing discourse, that the grand Plot, and whole design of it, moves chiefly on these two hinges. First, in confirming you, that the foundation of the Protestant Religion is built on <hi>God</hi>'s holy Word, the Scriptures; which we Protestants esteem to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Rule of Faith, and guide to our actions, and true Touch-stone to try all matters by, that relate to the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:199118:10"/> good of our Souls; as certainly containing in it all <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hings necessary to our salvation. The second thing I chiefly design to prove, is, that neither the Pope or the Popish Church are infallible: and these two shall make up the principle stories, in the little Model of this small <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uilding. The pretended infallibility of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is the grand perswasive Argument and lure to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ite men to it, and the strongest commanding Garrison <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n all the Popes power; and all other Arguments and Perswasions, are but like the small open Villages about <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>his Garrison, which must be servants to them, that are masters of it; and if a Papist can be but once convinc'd, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hat neither the Pope, nor the Popish Church are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>allible, they will soon be brought to reason, and our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining differences will not be very considerable: I <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hall therefore only lightly discourse on them, and shall <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o further trouble you, <hi>Madam,</hi> than briefly to answer <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hem in my own defence, as I meet them, or as they <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ollow me; and shall only do as the <hi>Wolf</hi> does when <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ursued, snap and bite in his own defence, against all <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>pposers, without altering his pace, or changing his <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oad: I shall neither meddle with the Papists, but as <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> meet them in the way, or towards making of my way <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o my two designed points, which are (as I said before) <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o prove the <hi>Scripture</hi> to be a perfect Rule of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uide</hi> to our <hi>actions;</hi> and to answer, as I go, the <hi>Papists</hi> main Arguments and Objections against it.</p>
            <p>Next, that 'tis against all <hi>Scripture,</hi> and <hi>Reason,</hi> that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>her the Pope, or the Popish Church should be <hi>infallible;</hi> which is the main design of this discourse: and if I can by <hi>God</hi>'s assistance make but the <hi>Papists</hi> believe <hi>reason,</hi> (when <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>gainst their own <hi>Church,</hi>) I doubt not but by this little Pigmie-discourse (as very dwarfish as 'tis,) not only to hinder many tottering <hi>Protestants</hi> from turning <hi>Papists,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ut to bring some stubborn <hi>Papists</hi> to turn <hi>Protestants,</hi> or <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t least not to have such an <hi>infallible good</hi> opinion of their Church, and so <hi>damnable a bad</hi> one of ours.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Madam,</hi> 'tis requisite that this my discourse <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hould be ended, as soon as your Patience; and therefore <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ll that I shall add, either to the excusing my self, or justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199118:11"/> Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> is, that thus far of this discourse being my own writing, I confess, deserves only my Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, and scarce your <hi>perusal;</hi> but the following dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course being extracted out of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves your reading, but needs not any Apology.</p>
            <p>And because I find the word <hi>Protestant</hi> is so badly and over-largely <hi>interpreted;</hi> I shall first acquaint you, that w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> are not to understand by the word <hi>Protestant,</hi> the Doctrin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Luther,</hi> or <hi>Calvin,</hi> or <hi>Geneva,</hi> or only the Articles o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but that wherein they all agre<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> with perfect Harmony, That the <hi>Bible</hi> is a perfect Rul<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of our Faith, and guide to our Actions; and this (afte<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> having made the most diligent and impartial search of th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> true way to Eternal happiness) I fully believe, and tha<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> we can never find any convincing satisfaction, but on thi<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Rock of <hi>God</hi>'s word, the <hi>Bible,</hi> which I conceive to b<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the only true Religion of Protestants.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Pope</hi> were indeed (what he unjustly says he is and the <hi>Papists</hi> unreasonably believe him to be,) an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible guide, then there needed no <hi>Bible;</hi> but if the <hi>Bible</hi> be then there needs no <hi>Pope:</hi> For if I were to go a Journey, an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> had a guide that could not err, what need I be taught th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> way? and having such a guide, what need I apply m<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> self to another? So that, in a word, let us inform ou<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> selves the best we can, and consider as much as we please the more consideration we take, the more confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we shall find, that there is no other foundation fo<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> a considering Christian to build an assured dependency on<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> than the <hi>Scriptures:</hi> For I am fully assur'd that <hi>God</hi> doe not (and therefore man ought not to) require of an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> more than this, to believe the <hi>Scripture</hi> to be the <hi>word o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> God,</hi> to use our best indeavours to find the true sense of it, and to live to our utmost according to it.</p>
            <p>This I am sure in reason we ought to believe; a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser choice than if I should guide my self by the <hi>Roman Churches Authority,</hi> and <hi>Infallibility;</hi> when really they have nothing of certainty, but their uncertainty; witnes<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Pope against Pope, Councils against Councils, some of their Fathers against others; and rather then fail, some against themselves▪ new Traditions inrolled, and old ones
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199118:11"/> Cashiered; in a word, one Church against another, and (if <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hat be not enough) the Church of one Age, against the Church of another: whereas the <hi>Scripture</hi> being true and unalterable, and containing all things necessary to our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; I am secure, that by believing nothing else, I shall believe no falshood in matter of Faith; and if I mistake the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rue sense of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and so fall into error; yet I am secured <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>rom any dangerous error, because whilst I am truly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ouring to find the true ground of <hi>Scripture,</hi> I cannot but <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>old my error without obstinacy, and be ready to forsake <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t, when more probable and true sense shall appear unto me: and then being assur'd, that all necessary truths are plainly <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>et down in <hi>Scripture,</hi> I am certain by believing the <hi>Scripture,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o believe all necessary <hi>truth:</hi> and he that does so, if his <hi>life</hi> be <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nswerable to his <hi>Faith,</hi> how is it possible he should fail of <hi>Salvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho the <hi>Roman Church</hi> pretend to be a perfect guide of <hi>Faith,</hi> and teacher of all <hi>Divine Truths;</hi> yet sure that <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>itle might much better, and more justly be given to the <hi>Scirptures,</hi> as their Teacher and Master.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Roman Church</hi> brags how ancient their Church is; but doubtless they cannot deny but the <hi>Scripture</hi> is more ancient, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>f they will but allow the <hi>Mother</hi> to be older than the <hi>Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Papists</hi> say their Church is a means of keeping Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians at unity, so are also the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> to those that be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ieve them in unity of belief, in matters necessary.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papists</hi> say their Church is <hi>Catholick:</hi> certainly the <hi>Scripture</hi> is more <hi>Catholick;</hi> for all true Christians in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal world do now, and ever did believe the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be the Word of <hi>God,</hi> so much at least, as to contain all things necessary to <hi>salvation;</hi> whereas the <hi>Papists</hi> say, They only are the true Church; and all other Christians (tho more than they) give them the lye for saying so.</p>
            <p>By following the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> I follow that whereby the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> prove their Churches <hi>Infallibility:</hi> For were it not for <hi>Scripture,</hi> what pretence could the <hi>Papists</hi> have for it, or what true Notion could they receive of it? So that by so dong, the <hi>Papists</hi> must plainly confess, That they themselves are surer of the Truth of <hi>Scripture,</hi> than of their <hi>Churches Authority;</hi> for we must be surer of the proof, than of the thing proved,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199118:12"/> or else 'tis no proof. So that following <hi>Scripture,</hi> I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that which must be true, if the <hi>Papists Church</hi> be true; for their Church allows it's truth: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if I follow the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, I must follow that, which tho the <hi>Scripture</hi> be true, may be false, nay more, must be false, if the <hi>Scripture</hi> be true, because the <hi>Scipture</hi> is against it. Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the <hi>Papists Church,</hi> I must be a <hi>servant</hi> to <hi>my Saviour,</hi> and a <hi>subject</hi> to <hi>my King,</hi> only at the <hi>pleasure</hi> of the <hi>Pope;</hi> and renounce <hi>my Allegiance,</hi> when the <hi>Popes</hi> will is to declare him an <hi>Heretick;</hi> nay, I must believe <hi>Vertue Vice,</hi> and <hi>Vice Vertue,</hi> if he pleases; for he both makes and unmakes <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> as he thinks <hi>convenient;</hi> witness the <hi>Apocripha,</hi> which hath not past for <hi>Canonical,</hi> but of late years, in the <hi>Papist<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Church, who interpret <hi>Scripture</hi> according to their <hi>Doctrine,</hi> but will not judge their <hi>Doctrine</hi> according to <hi>Scripture;</hi> for none like to weigh light <hi>Mony</hi> in true <hi>scales.</hi> In short, the <hi>Pope</hi> adds, and lessen, and interprets <hi>Divine Laws</hi> as he pleases; and they must stand for <hi>Laws,</hi> and be obeyed as <hi>such;</hi> so that in <hi>effect</hi> he rules his <hi>people</hi> by his own <hi>Laws,</hi> and his own <hi>Laws</hi> by his own <hi>Lawyers,</hi> his <hi>Clergy,</hi> who dare not speak nor uphold <hi>them,</hi> other than just such as the <hi>Pope</hi> would have <hi>them;</hi> and indeed Cardinal <hi>Riche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu</hi> gave the <hi>reason</hi> why more hold the <hi>Pope</hi> above the <hi>Councils,</hi> than the <hi>Councils</hi> above the <hi>Pope; Because the</hi> Pope <hi>gave Archbishopricks and Bishopricks, but the</hi> Councils <hi>had none to give:</hi> And tho the <hi>Papists</hi> say, his <hi>Holiness</hi> cannot err, yet let not the <hi>Papists</hi> forget what <hi>God</hi> says in the <hi>Scripture, if</hi> (not only the Pope, but if) <hi>angel from Heaven shall preach any thing against the</hi> Gospel of Christ, <hi>let him be accursed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In following the <hi>Scripture</hi> we have <hi>God's</hi> express com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and no colour of any prohibition: but to believe the <hi>Papish Church infallible,</hi> we have no <hi>Scripture-command</hi> at all, much less an express one.</p>
            <p>Following the <hi>Popish Church,</hi> we must believe many <hi>things</hi> not only above <hi>reason,</hi> but against <hi>reason,</hi> witness <hi>Transub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation;</hi> whereas following the <hi>Scripture,</hi> we shall believe Many <hi>mysteries,</hi> but no <hi>impossibilities;</hi> many things above our <hi>reason,</hi> but nothing against it. Nay, we need not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve any thing, which <hi>reason</hi> will not convince us we ought to believe▪ for <hi>reason</hi> will convince any sober <hi>Christian,</hi> that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:199118:12"/> the <hi>Scripture</hi> is the Word of <hi>God;</hi> and there's no <hi>reason</hi> can be greater than this, <hi>That God says it, therefore it must be true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, we <hi>Protestants</hi> believe that all things necessary to our <hi>salvation</hi> are evidently contain'd in <hi>Scripture,</hi> &amp; what is not there <hi>evidently</hi> contained, cannot be necessary to be <hi>believed;</hi> and our <hi>reason</hi> is just and clear, Because nothing can challenge our <hi>Belief,</hi> as to <hi>salvation,</hi> but what hath des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to us from our Blessed Saviour <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> by ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal and universal <hi>Tradition.</hi> Now nothing but <hi>Scripture</hi> hath thus descended to us, therefore nothing but <hi>Scripture</hi> can challenge our <hi>Belief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the grand difference between the <hi>Papists</hi> and us, concerning the <hi>Scripture,</hi> is this: We hold the <hi>Scripture</hi> to be the only <hi>perfect rule</hi> whereby to judge of <hi>controversies.</hi> The <hi>Papists</hi> say, That they acknowledge the <hi>Scuriptures</hi> to be a <hi>perfect rule:</hi> only they deny that it excludes unwritten <hi>Tradition;</hi> which in effect is this: they say, <hi>'Tis as perfect a Rule, as a Writing can be,</hi> only they deny it to <hi>be as perfect a Rule as a Writing may be.</hi> Either they must revoke their <hi>acknowledgment,</hi> or retract their <hi>contradiction</hi> of it, for both cannot possibly stand together: For if they will but stand to what they have granted, <hi>That</hi> Scripture <hi>is as perfect a Rule of Faith as a Writing can be,</hi> they must then grant it so <hi>compleat,</hi> as it needs no <hi>addition;</hi> and so <hi>evident</hi> that it needs no <hi>interpretation:</hi> for both these <hi>properties</hi> are requisite to a <hi>perfect Rule.</hi> And that a <hi>writing</hi> is capable of both these pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties and perfections, is most plain: for he that denies it, must say, <hi>that something may be spoken which cannot be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten;</hi> for if such a compleat <hi>evident rule of Faith</hi> may be delivered by word of mouth, as the <hi>Papists</hi> pretend may, &amp; is, <hi>and whatsoever is delivered by word of mouth, may also be written;</hi> then such a compleat and evident <hi>rule of Faith,</hi> may also be written: For the <hi>Argument</hi> is most plain, <hi>Whatsoever may be spoken may be written;</hi> a perfect <hi>rule of Faith</hi> has been spoken, therefore a perfect <hi>rule of Faith</hi> may be written. If the <hi>Papists</hi> cannot see this plain Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, they had best desire more light to be added to the <hi>Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Papists</hi> pretend their <hi>Church</hi> to be the <hi>infallible teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of all <hi>Divine Truths,</hi> and an <hi>infallible Interpreter</hi> of all <hi>obscurities</hi> in the <hi>Faith:</hi> But the <hi>Papists</hi> will, I hope give us
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199118:13"/> leave to admire, how they can pretend to Teach them in all places, without writing them down; that is certainly beyond the reach of their power to do, as well as our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief that 'tis to be done.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>Papists</hi> saying there must be a living authority beside the <hi>Scripture,</hi> or else controversies cannot be ended; <hi>Protestants</hi> answer: Necessary controversies are and may be decided; and if they be not, 'tis not the defect of the rule in <hi>Scripture,</hi> but the default of men; so that if necessary contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versies be ended, 'tis no matter if the unnecessary be not: for doubtless if <hi>God</hi> had required it, he would also have provided some means to effect it; but sure it does not stand with any reason it should be the <hi>Pope,</hi> because he cannot be a <hi>Judge,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>party:</hi> indeed in civil controversies, a Judge without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a party may end them; but in controversies of Religion, a Judge of necessity must be a concerned party; and I am sure the <hi>Pope</hi> to us is the chief, and most concerned party, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing really concerned as much as his Popedom is worth.</p>
            <p>Now we <hi>Protestants</hi> make the <hi>Papists</hi> this plain answer, that the means of agreeing differences, must necessarily be, either by the appointment of God, or men: men sure it cannot be, for then rational wise <hi>Protestants</hi> may do as well as <hi>Papists;</hi> for let the Papists shew us if they can, where <hi>God</hi> hath appointed that the Pope alone, or any confirm'd by the Pope, or that Society of Christians which adhere to him, shall be the <hi>infallible Judge</hi> of Controversies: we desire the Papists, if they can, to let us see any of those assertions plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly set down in <hi>Scripture,</hi> as in all reason a thing of this nature ought to be, or at least delivered with a full consent of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; nay let them so much as shew us where 'tis in plain terms taught by any one Father in Four hundred years after our blessed <hi>Saviour Christ:</hi> and if the Papists cannot do this, as we believe they cannot; where I pray is their either <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reason,</hi> that the Pope or his Councils should obtrude themselves as Judges over us Protestants.</p>
            <p>Next, we would desire to know from the Papists, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do certainly know, or not, the sense of those <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> by which they are led to the knowledge of their Church; for if they do not, how come they to know their Church is <hi>infallible?</hi> but if they do, then sure they ought to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199118:13"/> give us leave to have the same means and ability to know o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plain places in <hi>Scripture,</hi> which they have to know theirs: for if all <hi>Scriptures</hi> be obscure, how come they to know the sense of those places? but if some place of it be plain, why pray may not Protestants understand them as well as Papists?</p>
            <p>The Papists say, That the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are in themselves true and infallible, yet without the direction of the Church we have no certain means to know which <hi>Translations</hi> be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Canonical, or what is the true meaning of <hi>Scriptures:</hi> and this is the common <hi>Argument</hi> and general <hi>Belief</hi> of all Papists. To which the Protestants answer, That yet all these things must first be known, before we can know the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Church to be <hi>infallible:</hi> for the Papists cannot pretend any other proof of it, but only some Texts of Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical <hi>Scripture,</hi> truly interpreted; therefore either they must be mistaken in thinking there is no other means to know these things, but their Churches <hi>infallible</hi> direction; or else we must be excluded from all means of knowing her dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to be <hi>infallible:</hi> for the proof must be surer than the thing to be proved, or 'tis no proof. And upon better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration, I am confident the Papists dare not deny, but that 'tis most certain, <hi>Faith</hi> hath been given by other means than the Church: for sure they will not say, that <hi>Adam</hi> received Faith by the Church, nor <hi>Abraham,</hi> nor <hi>Job,</hi> who received Faith by Revelation; and also the Holy Apostles, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Faith by the Miracles and Preaching of our Blessed Saviour: So that you see, and they cannot deny, but their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Doctrine is contradictory. And to make it yet plainer, I desire to know of the Papists, if they should meet with a man that believed neither <hi>Scripture, Church,</hi> nor <hi>God,</hi> but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares he is both ready and willing to believe them all, if the Papist can shew him sufficient <hi>grounds</hi> to build his <hi>Faith</hi> upon; will the Papist tell such a man, there are no certain <hi>grounds</hi> how he may be converted to their Church, or there are? if the Papists say there are none, they make Religion an uncertain thing: but if they say there are, then they must necessarily either argue woman-like, that their Church is <hi>infallible,</hi> because it is <hi>infallible;</hi> or else shew there are other certain <hi>grounds</hi> besides saying the Church is <hi>infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> to prove its <hi>Infallibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:199118:14"/>
            <p>The <hi>Papists</hi> demand of the <hi>Protestants, If they believe the Apostles wrote all the Scriptures:</hi> for if they did not, how come we to call and believe them <hi>Apostolical,</hi> and not the <hi>Writings</hi> of those that writ them? To which we answer; <hi>Though all the Scriptures were not written by the Apostles themselves, yet they were all confirm'd by them; and tho a Clerk writes a Statute, and the King, Lords and Commons confirm it in Parliament; I believe they would esteem it very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to call it the Statute of such a Clerk, tho writ by him, but an Act of Parliament, because it was confirm'd by all their censents, and becomes their Act, not the Clerks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Papists</hi> desire us to tell them <hi>in what Language the Scriptures remained uncorrupted;</hi> and we desire them to satisfie us <hi>whether it be necessary to know it, or not necessary:</hi> if it be not, I hope we may do well without it; but if it be necessary, we desire first that <hi>they</hi> will please to tell us what became of their <hi>Church</hi> for One thousand five hundred Years together, all which time they must confess, they had no certainty of <hi>Scripture;</hi> till the time that Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 8th. set forth their approved Edition of the vulgar <hi>Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and none sure can have the <hi>confidence</hi> to deny, but that there was great <hi>variety</hi> of <hi>Copies</hi> currant in divers parts of their <hi>Church,</hi> and read so; which Copies might be false in some things, but more than one sort of them could not possibly be true in all things. And Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> his <hi>Bible</hi> differ'd from Pope <hi>Clement</hi> his <hi>Bible,</hi> in a multitude of places; which makes us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to be satisfied of the <hi>Papists,</hi> whether before Pope <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Quintus</hi> his time, their Church had any defined Canon of <hi>Scriptures</hi> or not: for if they had not, then 'tis most <hi>evident</hi> that their Church was a most <hi>excellent keeper</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> for Fifteen hundred years together, that had not all that time defin'd what was <hi>Scripture,</hi> and what was not; but if the <hi>Papists</hi> say they had, then we demand, Was that set forth by Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> or was it set forth by Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> or if by a third <hi>different</hi> from them both, why do they not name him? if it were that set forth by Pope <hi>Sixtus,</hi> then 'tis now condemn'd by Pope <hi>Clement;</hi> if that of <hi>Clement,</hi> 'twas condemned by that of <hi>Sixtus:</hi> So that error must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily be betwixt <hi>them,</hi> let <hi>them</hi> chuse which <hi>side they please.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:199118:14"/>
            <p>And for the Book of <hi>Maccabees,</hi> I hope they will allow it <hi>defin'd Canonical</hi> before St. <hi>Gregorie</hi>'s time, though he would not allow it <hi>Canonical,</hi> but only for the <hi>Edification</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p>We further desire to be satisfied of the <hi>Papists,</hi> if the Books of <hi>Ecclesiasticus,</hi> and <hi>Wisdom,</hi> and the Epistle to St. <hi>James,</hi> were by the holy <hi>Apostles</hi> approved Canonical, or not: if they were approved by the <hi>Apostles</hi> Canonical, sure the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> cannot deny, but they had a sufficient <hi>difinition</hi> and <hi>authority,</hi> not to question them, and therefore <hi>err'd</hi> in doing so. And if they were not approved Canonical by the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> with what <hi>impudence</hi> dare the <hi>Roman</hi> Church now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them as <hi>Canonical,</hi> and yet pretend that all their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is <hi>Apostolical?</hi> And if they say these Books were not questioned, they should do well to tell which Books they mean, which were not always known to be <hi>Canonical,</hi> but have afterwards been receiveed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be such: so that this <hi>Argument</hi> reaches those, as well as these.</p>
            <p>And further we are to consider, that there is not the same <hi>reasons</hi> for the Churches <hi>absolute Infallibility,</hi> as for the <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Scriptures:</hi> for if the Church falls into an error, it may be reformed by comparing it with the Rules of the <hi>Apostles</hi> Doctrine in <hi>Scripture;</hi> but if the <hi>Apostles</hi> have err'd in delivering the Doctrine of Christianity in <hi>Scripture;</hi> then the <hi>Roman</hi> Church cannot be <hi>infallible:</hi> For <hi>Apostles, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Canonical Writers,</hi> and the foundation of the Church, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> says 'tis built upon the foundation of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles</hi> and <hi>Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to conclude this part of my discourse in very few words, let the <hi>Papists</hi> answer, if they can, but these five words. <hi>All Scripture is Divinely inspired.</hi> Let them shew us so much for the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and shew us if they can, where 'tis written in <hi>Scripture,</hi> that all the decrees of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Church</hi> are Divinely inspired, and all our <hi>Controversies</hi> will be at an end: but I believe they can never do that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out another <hi>Transubstantiation-Miracle</hi> of words.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papists</hi> desire us to shew them an exact <hi>Catalogue</hi> of our <hi>fundamentals;</hi> to which we answer, That <hi>God</hi> may be suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently known to one, and not sufficiently declared to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and consequently, that may be fundamental and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:199118:15"/> to one, which is not to another; which variety of <hi>circumstances</hi> renders it impossible to set down an exact <hi>Catalogue</hi> of <hi>Fundamentals:</hi> for God requires more of them to whom he gives more, and less of those to whom he gives less; more of a <hi>commander</hi> of a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> than a poor simple <hi>Turnspit.</hi> 'Tis a plain revelation of <hi>God</hi> to us Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, that the <hi>Sacrament of the Eucharist</hi> should be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred in both kinds, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. &amp; that the publick <hi>Hymns</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> of the Church should be in such a <hi>Language</hi> as is most for Edification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15, 16. yet the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> not seeing this, by reason of the <hi>vail,</hi> would be <hi>very angry</hi> if we told <hi>them</hi> 'twould <hi>prejudice</hi> their <hi>supposed Infallibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We read in St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> that the <hi>Gospel</hi> was to be Preacht <hi>to all Nations;</hi> and this was a <hi>truth</hi> revealed before our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours</hi> Ascention: yet if the Church had been asked, before the conversion of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> they would have certainly told you, it had not been necessary to <hi>teach all Nations;</hi> for 'tis most apparent out of <hi>Acts</hi> 11. they all believed so, until St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was better informed by a vision from <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the conversion of <hi>Cornelius;</hi> and then they turn'd quite of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering belief, and esteemed it necessary to <hi>teach all Nations;</hi> and yet were still a Church. The Papists are pleased to say, the Protestants differ in <hi>Fundamentals;</hi> which indeed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to us very <hi>irrational:</hi> For if they say, We Protestants differ in <hi>Fundamentals,</hi> how then can they say, We are <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of the same Church, one with another, more than they are with ours, or ours with theirs? and why do they <hi>object</hi> our <hi>difference</hi> more with one another, than with themselves? and if we do not differ in <hi>Fundamentals,</hi> why do they up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid us with <hi>Fundamental differences</hi> amongst our selves? We believe the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> cannot perish, yet we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve she may and did <hi>err,</hi> as I prov'd just before: but thus much we Protestants declare in general, That we esteem it sufficient for any mans <hi>salvation,</hi> to believe <hi>God's</hi> Word, the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and that it contains all <hi>things necessary to our salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and that we do our utmost <hi>endeavours</hi> to find, believe, and follow the true sense of it; and being we are sure that all that is any way necessary is there, believing all that is there, we are sure we believe all that is necessary.</p>
            <p>And therefore 'tis but reasonable to say, that any private
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:199118:15"/> person, who truly believes the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and heartily endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to know the Will of <hi>God,</hi> and to do it, is as secure, nay <hi>securer</hi> from the danger of <hi>erring in Fundamentals,</hi> than the <hi>Roman</hi> Church▪ for 'tis impossible any man so <hi>qualified</hi> should fall into an <hi>error</hi> that can prove <hi>damnable</hi> to him; for <hi>God</hi> requires no more of any man to his <hi>salvation,</hi> but only his true and best endeavours to be <hi>saved.</hi> And for the Papists <hi>Sacrament of Confession,</hi> which they hold is so <hi>absolute</hi> and <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessary,</hi> and so much upbraid us for the want of it; we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer: We know no such <hi>absolute necessity of it;</hi> but yet we hold, we must not only <hi>confess our sins, but forsake them,</hi> or we shall not find <hi>mercy:</hi> And we Protestants farther believe, that they that <hi>confess their sins, shall find mercy,</hi> though they only confess them to <hi>God,</hi> and not to Man: And more, that they who confess them both to <hi>God</hi> and Man, and do not in time forsake them, shall not find <hi>mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so for the Papists <hi>Sacrament of Repentance for Remissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of sins;</hi> tho we Protestants know no such, yet we allow &amp; observe the same Duty, but <hi>publick</hi> before the Church; which was the <hi>constant practice</hi> of the primitive Church; and <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanus</hi> himself, though so great a Champion for the Papists, writes, That the <hi>confession</hi> then used, was before the Church; and that <hi>Auricular confession</hi> was not then in the World.</p>
            <p>The Papists will tell you that our <hi>Bishops</hi> have not the true power of <hi>Ordination:</hi> but <hi>that has</hi> been so <hi>clearly answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and so <hi>truly proved at large</hi> by so many already, as I shall not need here so much as to name it: only let me in a word <hi>remember</hi> the Papists, that they cannot well deny, but that the <hi>Donatists</hi> themselves, whom the Papists esteemed as bad as us, as being <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schismaticks;</hi> yet St. <hi>Austin,</hi> and <hi>Optatus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> did both acknowledge that they had the same <hi>Baptism, Creed,</hi> and <hi>Sacrament;</hi> and that these <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natist</hi> Fathers, tho <hi>Schismaticks</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> gave true Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, or else some of these were not then esteemed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments;</hi> therefore let them take which they please, there must be error of one side.</p>
            <p>The Papists pretend they have an unanswerable <hi>Objection</hi> against Protestants, which is, <hi>That we have discords in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith, without any means of agreement:</hi> To which we answer, <hi>That the Scripture does not let us want solid means of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:199118:16"/> agreement in matters nessary to salvation;</hi> and for our agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all controversies of <hi>Religion,</hi> either they must say we have means to agree about them, or we have not: if they say we have, why did they before deny it? if they say we have no <hi>means,</hi> why are they so unjust to find <hi>fault</hi> with us for not <hi>agreeing,</hi> when <hi>they themselves</hi> say we have no <hi>means</hi> to <hi>agree?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for a Plaister to this Saor, they are so extraordinary civil, as to tell us, <hi>we may come to their Church;</hi> and they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in <hi>matters of faith:</hi> But the plain truth of it is, that they define all <hi>matters of faith</hi> to be those wherein they agree; so that to say the <hi>Roman</hi> Church does agree in <hi>matters of faith,</hi> is but to say, they do agree in those things they do agree in: and sure they cannot deny, but we <hi>Protestants</hi> do the same.</p>
            <p>But we must desire the <hi>Papists</hi> to give us leave to tell them, that they most grosly mistake, if they say, they agree in <hi>matters of Faith:</hi> as for proof; some of them hold it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Faith, to take the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> others 'tis against Faith to refuse that Oath.</p>
            <p>Some hold it of <hi>Faith,</hi> that the <hi>Pope</hi> is Head of the <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Divine Law;</hi> others the contrary: some hold it of Faith that the <hi>blessed Virgin</hi> was free from <hi>actual sin,</hi> others the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; some that the <hi>Popes</hi> power over Princes in Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities is <hi>de fide,</hi> others the contrary: some that 'tis univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal <hi>Tradition</hi> that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was conceived in <hi>actual sin,</hi> others the contrary. And how the <hi>Jesuits</hi> and <hi>Franciscans,</hi> and other Orders differ to this day, I am sure needs no <hi>memorandum;</hi> and the best Jest of all is, the <hi>Papists</hi> have not so much as yet agreed in their very pretended means of <hi>agreement,</hi> and yet have the <hi>confidency</hi> to pretended an <hi>Ʋnity</hi> more than the <hi>Protestants;</hi> for some of them say, The <hi>Pope</hi> with a <hi>Council</hi> may determine all <hi>Controversies,</hi> others deny it: Some hold, That a general <hi>Council,</hi> without a <hi>Pope,</hi> may do so; others deny this: Others say, Both in conjunction are <hi>infallible Determiners,</hi> others deny this: And some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Papists</hi> hold, The acceptation of the Decrees of <hi>Councils</hi> by the Universal Church, is the only way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide <hi>Controversies;</hi> which others deny, by denying their Church to be <hi>infallible;</hi> and yet every part pretends to be part of the Church.</p>
            <p>In a word, can the <hi>Papish</hi> deny, but that there has been
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:199118:16"/> Popes against Popes, Councils against Councils; Nay, Councils confirmed by Popes, against Popes confirmed by Councils: And lastly, the Church of some Ages, against the Church of other Ages? And since every part of the Body is so out of order, methinks they should not brag of so perfect a health as they do.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papists</hi> say (and do but say it) that their <hi>Doctrine</hi> is held <hi>Catholick;</hi> and therefore they esteem it an <hi>insolent mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of us <hi>Protestants,</hi> to dispute against the <hi>practice</hi> of the whole Church. First, <hi>That their Doctrine is Catholick;</hi> we answer, <hi>That the greatest number of Christians in the world deny it;</hi> so that they cannot truly say, we dispute against the <hi>practice</hi> of the whole Church. And farther we say, <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing we should in Complement to them grant, that their Church is Catholick and Ʋniversal;</hi> yet we say, That is no sufficient proof it came Originally from the <hi>Apostles;</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness the Doctrine of the <hi>Millenaries,</hi> and the necessity of the <hi>Eucharist</hi> for <hi>Infants;</hi> which was generally taught by the <hi>Ʋniversal Church,</hi> &amp; believed as an <hi>Apostolical Tradition,</hi> but yet contradicted by the <hi>Ʋniversal Church</hi> afterwards: This, I am sure, the <hi>Papists</hi> dare not deny; so that we una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably cast the <hi>Papists</hi> upon this <hi>Rock, That they must either conclude the</hi> Apostles <hi>were Fountains of contradictory Doctrines, or that the</hi> Universal Doctrine <hi>of the present Church is no sufficient proof that it came originally from the</hi> Apostles, <hi>because the Church Ʋniversal of one time, and the Church Ʋniversal of another time did differ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, for their saying, <hi>'tis insolent madness to dispute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the practice of the whole Church;</hi> First, we are sure, we can bring more Christian witnesses that deny they are the <hi>whole Church,</hi> than they can bring to prove it: but suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing we were as mad as they say we are, and would have us to be, <hi>to dispute against the whole practice of the Church;</hi> yet I hope we may desire to know of the <hi>Papists,</hi> if they can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but that 'twas the practice of the <hi>whole Church</hi> in St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin</hi>'s time, and esteemed then an <hi>Apostolical Tradition</hi> even by St. <hi>Austin</hi> himself, that the <hi>Eucharist</hi> should be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred to <hi>Infants?</hi> And then let them tell us, Whether it be <hi>insolent madness to dispute against the practice of the whole Church,</hi> or is it not? If it be not, why do they accuse us for it? But if it be <hi>insolent madness,</hi> how mad
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:199118:17"/> and <hi>insolent</hi> is the Papists Church, not only to <hi>dispute</hi> against this <hi>practice</hi> of the <hi>Ʋniversal Church,</hi> of administring the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charist</hi> to <hi>Infants,</hi> but utterly abolishing the practice of it?</p>
            <p>So that the very worst the Papists can say of us, allowing what they say to be true, is, <hi>that we but do, what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves own already to have done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho the Papists are pleased to say that the Holy <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and ancient <hi>Fathers,</hi> assign <hi>separation</hi> from the visible Church as a mark of <hi>Heresie,</hi> yet they cannot shew one plain Text of <hi>Scripture</hi> to confirm it.</p>
            <p>And for the Papists bragging of the <hi>Antiquity</hi> and <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versality</hi> of their Churches <hi>Doctrine,</hi> (tho we allow it very <hi>ancient,</hi> bating the <hi>primitive times</hi>) we answer first as to its <hi>Antiquity,</hi> we desire to see what <hi>Antiquity</hi> they can shew for their giving the Communion but in one kind, when they know that the <hi>administring</hi> it in both kinds, was the <hi>practice</hi> of the Church for a Thousand years after <hi>Christ;</hi> what An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity for the lawfulness and expediency of the <hi>Latine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice;</hi> for the present use of <hi>Indulgences;</hi> for the Popes power in <hi>Temporalities over Princes;</hi> for the Picturing the <hi>Trinity;</hi> for the lawfulness of worshipping <hi>Pictures and Images;</hi> for their <hi>Beads;</hi> for their whole worship of the <hi>blessed Virgin;</hi> for their <hi>Oblations,</hi> in the notion of <hi>Sacrifices</hi> to her and other <hi>Saints;</hi> for their saying <hi>Pater Nosters</hi> and <hi>Creeds</hi> to the Honour of them, and <hi>Ave Maries</hi> to the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> for the <hi>infallibility</hi> of the Bishop or Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> for their <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the blessed Virgins Immunity from actual sin; for the necessity of <hi>Auricular confession;</hi> for the necessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Priests <hi>intention</hi> to obtain <hi>benefit</hi> by any of their <hi>Sacraments;</hi> and lastly, for their licentious Doctrine, in hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that tho a man lives and dies without the practice of any Christian Vertue, and with the Habits of many damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sins unmortified; yet if at the last moment of his life he has any sorrow for his sins, and joyn confession to it, he shall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be saved:</hi> This is a Doctrine may keep many Souls out of Heaven, but I doubt will scarce carry any one there. So that the Papists Doctrine being ancient, is nothing, as long as 'tis <hi>evident</hi> that they hold many <hi>dangerous errors:</hi> As for instance, the <hi>Millenaries,</hi> and the <hi>Communicating Infants</hi> was more <hi>ancient</hi> than their Doctrine; and 'tis plain that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:199118:17"/> unless it be <hi>absolute</hi> and <hi>primative,</hi> is not a certain sign of true Doctrine, and the very Apostles themselves, assure us, that in their days the mystery of Iniquity was working.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papists</hi> demand how comes it to pass that their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine is so Universal, (forgetting that weeds spread faster than good herbs:) And we ask them how the <hi>errours</hi> of the <hi>Millenaries,</hi> and the <hi>Communicating Infants</hi> became so universal? let them tell us this, and we will tell them that: for what is done in some, may be done in others.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papists</hi> ask us where our Ch. was before <hi>Luther;</hi> and tell us, because 'twas no Ch. before him, therefore it can be no true Church at all. To which we answer, That this cause is no cause: for tho <hi>Luther</hi> had no being before <hi>Luther,</hi> yet none can deny, but that he was when he was, tho he could not be before he was. So there may be a true Church after <hi>Luther,</hi> tho there was none for some Ages before him: as since <hi>Columbus</hi> his time there have been Christians in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> tho there were none for many Ages before. For it does not follow, that nothing but a Church can possibly get a Church, nor that the present being of a true Church depends necessarily upon the perpetuity of a Church in all Ages. For though I cannot deny the Churches perpetui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet that's not here necessary to rur difference: but that a false Church (by Gods providence over-ruling it) may preserve a means of confuting their own Heresies, and so reduce men to Truth, and raise a true Church, (I mean the integrity of the Word of God with Men.) Thus the <hi>Jews</hi> preserve means to make men <hi>Christians,</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> preserve means to make men <hi>Protestants,</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> false Church (as the <hi>Romans</hi> call it) preserves men <hi>Papists.</hi> Nor does it appear that the perpetuity of the <hi>Church</hi> is the truth of the <hi>Papists Church:</hi> for they speak as if they were the only Christians in the World before <hi>Luther;</hi> when the whole World knows, that this is but talk, and that there were other Christians besides the <hi>Papists</hi> that might have perpetuated the <hi>Church,</hi> tho there had not been then one <hi>Papist</hi> in being. For sure there was a Catholick Church before the <hi>Roman</hi> one.</p>
            <p>Next, the <hi>Papists</hi> say, To hold that the Visible
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:199118:18"/>
               <hi>Church is not perpetual, is a Heresie;</hi> so that <hi>Luther</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation being but particular, and not universal, nor but of late date; it can have nothing to do with the visible and perpetual Church. Which the <hi>Protestants</hi> answer thus. <hi>To say the visible Church is not perpetual, is properly a Heresie;</hi> but the <hi>Papists</hi> cannot deny, but that the <hi>Apostles</hi> who preach'd the <hi>Gospel</hi> in the beginning, did believe the <hi>Church universal,</hi> tho their preaching at the beginning was not so. So <hi>Luther</hi> also might well believe the <hi>Ʋniversal Church,</hi> though his <hi>Reformation</hi> was but particular; the Church in the Apostles time being universal <hi>de jure</hi> of right, but not <hi>de facto</hi> in fact.</p>
            <p>Nor did <hi>Luther</hi> and his followers (as the <hi>Papists</hi> are pleased to mis-call many <hi>Protestants</hi>) forsake the whole Church, but the <hi>corruptions</hi> of it, in renouncing some of their corrupt practices; and this the <hi>Protestants</hi> say they did without <hi>Schism,</hi> because they had cause to do it; and no man can have cause to be a <hi>Schismatick,</hi> because he is only one who leaves the Church without a cause: for 'tis not only <hi>separation,</hi> but a <hi>causeless separation</hi> from the Church, that is <hi>Schismatical:</hi> and I think 'twill not be amiss, before I go any farther, to distinguish the difference between <hi>Heresie</hi> and <hi>Schism. Heresie is an obstinate defence of any error a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any necessary Article of the Christian Faith. Schism is a causeless separation of one part of the Church from another.</hi> Now we <hi>Protestants</hi> say still, That we never forsook the whole Church, or the external Communion of it, but only that part of it which is corrupted, and is to be fear'd will still continue so, <hi>viz. The Papists Church;</hi> and forsook not, but only reformed another part, which part they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves were. And sure the <hi>Papists</hi> will not say, the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> forsook themselves, nor their own Communion: and therefore the <hi>Papists</hi> Argument must be very weak, in urging that the <hi>Protestants</hi> joyned themselves to no other part of the Church, therefore they must separate from the whole Church; which the <hi>Protestants</hi> say is a false conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, in as much as they themselves were part of it, and still continue so; and therefore the <hi>Protestants</hi> could no more separate from the whole, than from themselves.</p>
            <p>So that by the rule of <hi>Reason,</hi> if <hi>Protestants</hi> be <hi>Schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:199118:18"/> because they differ from one part of the <hi>visible Church;</hi> by the same reason the <hi>Protestants</hi> may say that the <hi>Roman Church</hi> is in a manner made up of <hi>Schismaticks:</hi> for the <hi>Jesuits</hi> are Schismaticks from the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans</hi> from the <hi>Jesuits,</hi> and the <hi>Jesuits</hi> from the <hi>Canonists;</hi> the <hi>Franciscans</hi> from the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and the <hi>Dominicans</hi> from the <hi>Franciscans:</hi> for all these (as the world knows) differ in point of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and betwixt them there is an <hi>ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcilable contradiction;</hi> and therefore one part must be in error. And if the <hi>Papists</hi> will but stand to justifie what they declare as truth, <hi>That every error against a revealed Truth is a Heresie;</hi> they holding for certain as a revealed Truth, the Immaculate Conception of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> then consequently the <hi>Dominicans</hi> that hold and declare it an error in Doctrine, must necessarily hold a Heresie. Now it may be a fault to be in error, because it many times pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a fault; but sure <hi>Protestants</hi> forsaking error, it cannot be a sin, unless to be in error, be a Vertue: So hardly do <hi>Papists</hi> deal with us <hi>Protestants,</hi> as they will either damn us in making us follow their false opinions, or else brand us as <hi>Schismaticks</hi> for leaving them.</p>
            <p>And yet the rational sort of <hi>Papists</hi> can hardly deny, but the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> must be a safer <hi>Religion</hi> than theirs, in <hi>worshipping Pictures,</hi> in <hi>Invocating Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> in <hi>denying the Lay-men</hi> the <hi>Communion in both kinds,</hi> as was commanded by our <hi>blessed Saviour; in celebrating</hi> their <hi>Church-Service in an unknown Tongue,</hi> which was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by St. <hi>Paul;</hi> in <hi>adoring the Sacrament:</hi> and in <hi>all these</hi> a rational <hi>Papist</hi> cannot deny, but he is on the more danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous side, as to the committing of sin; and the <hi>Protestant</hi> in the more secure way, as to the avoiding it.</p>
            <p>For in all these things, if <hi>Protestants</hi> say true, the <hi>Papists</hi> do that which is impious; but on the other side, if the <hi>Papists</hi> were in the right, yet the <hi>Protestants</hi> might be secure enough too: for their fault would be only this, that they should only not do some things which the <hi>Papists</hi> themselves confess is not altogether necessary to be done.</p>
            <p>And truly the <hi>Protestants</hi> are so Charitably civil, as only to say of <hi>Papists,</hi> as St. <hi>Austin</hi> did of the <hi>Donatists, That
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:199118:19"/> Catholicks approved the Doctrine of the</hi> Donatists, <hi>but abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their Heresie of Rebaptization. So Protestants</hi> approve the <hi>Fundamental</hi> and <hi>necessary Truths</hi> which the <hi>Papists</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, by which many good Souls among them may be saved; but abhor the many <hi>superstitions</hi> they use in their <hi>Religion.</hi> And supposing these <hi>Errors</hi> of the <hi>Popish Church</hi> were in themselves not damnable, to them that believe as they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess; yet for us <hi>Protestants</hi> to profess what we do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and esteem those as Divine Truths, which we believe not to be either Divine or true; would be doubtless dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable as to us: for 'tis certain, Two men may do the same thing, and it may be sinful to one, and not to the other: as suppose a married Woman gives herself out to be a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and one knowing her Husband to be alive, marries her, doubtless his injoyment of her was adulterous: but a second man comes, and after seeing her pretended Husband buried, marries her, and dies without the least informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her first Husbands being then alive; his ignorance sure protected him from sin, and the second Husbands know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the sin he acted, condemned him of Adultery; &amp; tho his fault might be palliated with some excuses, yet it can never be defended by any just Apoligy. And so tho we read in Scripture, that it was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Judgment, that meat offered to Idols might lawfully be eaten; yet he says; <hi>if any should eat it with a doubtful Conscience, he should sin, and be condemned for so doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And supposing we <hi>Protestants</hi> ought not to have forsook the <hi>Papists</hi> Church, for sin, and errours, if she had not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd and imposed them on us; yet since she does main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them with such obstinacy, and imposes them with such tyranny, we ought certainly to say with St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>John, 'Tis better to forsake men than God;</hi> and leave the <hi>Popish Church-Communion,</hi> rather than commit or profess <hi>known errors</hi> as <hi>Divine Truths;</hi> for as the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> tells us, that to say <hi>The Lord hath said so, when the Lord hath not said so,</hi> is a high presumption, and great sin, be the matter never so small; and therefore when St. <hi>Paul</hi> spoke concerning Virgins abstaining from <hi>marriage,</hi> he said, <hi>He had no commandment of the Lord, but I declare my own judgment of it.</hi> Now if St. <hi>Paul</hi> had given this as God's
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:199118:19"/> command, surely we might have justly contradicted him, and made a distinction between <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> and <hi>Humane Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that for a <hi>Protestant</hi> to abide in the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> is so far from securing him from <hi>errour,</hi> as that if I or any <hi>Protestant</hi> should continue in it, I am confident I could not be saved by it: and the reason is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the <hi>Papists</hi> will not admit of my Communion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out professing the entire Popish Doctrine to be true: and profess this I cannot, but I must perpetually exulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate my Conscience: &amp; tho the <hi>errours</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> were not in themselves damnable, yet for me to resist <hi>known Truths,</hi> and to continue in the <hi>Profession of known er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and falshoods,</hi> is certainly a capital sin, and of great affinity with the sin which shall never be forgiven.</p>
            <p>In short, if the <hi>errours</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> did not warrant our departure, yet the tyrannous imposition of them would be our sufficient justification; for they force us either to forsake the <hi>Papists Communion,</hi> or profess as <hi>Gospel-truths</hi> what our <hi>Conscience</hi> assures us is very little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin to them: so that the <hi>Protestants</hi> were oblig'd to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake those <hi>errours</hi> of the <hi>Popish Church,</hi> and not the <hi>Church,</hi> but the <hi>errours;</hi> and we <hi>Protestants</hi> did, and do still conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue <hi>members</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> having only left what appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red most plain to us to be <hi>superstitious</hi> and <hi>impious.</hi> And we separate no more from the <hi>Popish Church,</hi> thant she has separated from the <hi>Ancient Church:</hi> and indeed, to speak properly, our difference is more against the <hi>Court,</hi> than <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> which has introduced so many new ceremonies and practises in the <hi>Popish Church,</hi> as was never heard nor practised in the <hi>Primitive Times:</hi> as for one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of a Thousand, I might give you <hi>Their deny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng the Cup to the Laity,</hi> which was never practised in the Church a Thousand years after our <hi>Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But because the <hi>Papists</hi> brag so much of, and depend so entirely on the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of their Church, I shall pass by their Out-works, and search a little into this their Grand Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, the <hi>Infallibility of their Church:</hi> for except they prove that, they prove nothing; but in proving that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:199118:20"/> they prove all: and if the <hi>Papists</hi> could satisfie me either by <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reason,</hi> that their <hi>Church</hi> is <hi>infallible,</hi> I should not only be of their Church to morrow, but repent I was not sooner: but really by all that I ever heard or read for their making it good, I find cause only to admire their <hi>confidence,</hi> but not at all to esteem their <hi>reasons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The cheif <hi>method</hi> they take, and <hi>degrees</hi> they use, to prove the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of their <hi>Church,</hi> are by <hi>whole-sale</hi> these, First, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was <hi>head</hi> and <hi>cheif</hi> amongst the <hi>Apostles;</hi> and there was given to him and his Successors by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> Universal Authority over his Militent <hi>Church;</hi> That the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Successor, and has his <hi>Authority of Ʋniversal Bishop;</hi> and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Roman Church</hi> being built upon this <hi>Rock</hi> is <hi>infallible▪</hi> all which I doubt not but to prove to be inconsistent with, and contradictory both to <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the first point of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s being Head of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles,</hi> which the <hi>Papists</hi> all stile him, and say he was called from thence <hi>Cephas,</hi> which is derived from the <hi>Greek</hi> word <hi>Head:</hi> it is a most gross mistake; for <hi>Cephas</hi> is a <hi>Syriack</hi> word that signifies <hi>Stone;</hi> but this is only by the by. Now we <hi>Protestants</hi> say, tho we allow St. <hi>Peter</hi> might have <hi>primacy of Order,</hi> yet we cannot grant he had <hi>supremacy of power</hi> over the other <hi>Apostles;</hi> for sure it cannot stand with the least reason, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> should have <hi>authority</hi> over all the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and yet never act the least <hi>authority</hi> over any one of them.</p>
            <p>Nor is it reasonable to believe, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> having <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> over all the <hi>Apostles</hi> for above 25 years together, should never shew the least power over any of them all that time, nor so much as receive the lest subjection from them: sure any one must think this as strange, &amp; unreason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as if a King of <hi>England</hi> for 25 years together should not do one act of Regality among his Subjects, nor receive any one acknowledgment from them.</p>
            <p>Nor sure is it less strange &amp; unreasonable, that the <hi>Papists</hi> should so many Ages after, know this so certainly as they pretend they do, and yet that the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves, after that these words were spoak in their hearing by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue whereof St. <hi>Peter</hi> is pretended to be made their <hi>head,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:199118:20"/> should still be so ignorant of it, as to question our <hi>Saviour, which of them should be the greatest?</hi> By which sure we may rationally conclude, they did not then know; for if they did, their question had been needless, and superfluous, in desiring to be taught, what they already knew.</p>
            <p>And what yet appears more <hi>strange</hi> than all, is, that our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> should not have helped them out of their <hi>error,</hi> by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them St. <hi>Peter</hi> was the man; but rather confirmed them in the contrary, by saying, <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles exercise Authority over them, but it should not be so among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, it is as <hi>strange</hi> and <hi>unreasonable,</hi> that St. <hi>Paul</hi> should so far forget both St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and himself, as in men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning so often St. <hi>Peter,</hi> he should still do it without as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing him any title of Honour: Nor does it stand with <hi>reason,</hi> that St. <hi>Paul</hi> speaking of the several <hi>degrees</hi> of men in the <hi>Church,</hi> should omit giving St. <hi>Peter</hi> the highest, if it had been his due, but place him in the same <hi>rank</hi> and <hi>equipage</hi> with the rest of the <hi>Apostles:</hi> for St. <hi>Paul</hi> says <hi>God hath appointed</hi> (not first St. <hi>Peter,</hi> then the rest of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles) but <hi>first Apostles, secondly Prophets;</hi> now certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if <hi>Apostles</hi> were all first, that is, all equal, how could one be in greater power than the other?</p>
            <p>But besides all this, though we should grant against all these probabilities, and many more, that <hi>Optatus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> meant that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was Head of the <hi>Apostles;</hi> yet sure the <hi>Papists</hi> are still very far from proving, the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> was to be so at all, much less by <hi>Divine right,</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor to St. <hi>Peter</hi> in his Headship and Authority. For what incongruity is there, if we say that <hi>Optatus</hi> might suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed St. <hi>Peter</hi> as his Heir and Successor, in that part of his Government of that particular Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> (as sure he did even whilst St. <hi>Peter</hi> was living) and yet that neither he, nor any man was to succeed him in his <hi>Apostleship,</hi> nor in the <hi>Government of the Church Ʋniversal?</hi> as tho a Bishop should leave his Son Heir to all he died possessed of; I hope you will not conclude, therefore he must necessarily suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him in the Bishoprick he died seized of. The <hi>Apostles</hi> were men all called, and Divinely inspired by the <hi>Holy Ghost;</hi> which was the immediate gift of <hi>God,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could not be left as a Legary by man; for though it be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:199118:21"/> in any mans power to leave his Estate, yet 'tis in no mans power to leave to his Son his acquir'd parts at his death. 'Tis further worth your observing, and special notice, that <hi>St. Peter</hi> himself and the rest of the Apostles, by laying the Foundation of the <hi>Church,</hi> were to be themselves the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of it; and are accordingly so called in <hi>Scripture.</hi> And therefore as in a building 'tis incongruous that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations should succeed foundations, so it may be in the <hi>Church,</hi> that Apostles should succeed Apostles, the <hi>Church</hi> being built upon Apostles and Prophets.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed does the grand argument of the <hi>Papists</hi> for their <hi>Pope,</hi> extend any further in reallity then the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome:</hi> for thus goes their main argument: St. <hi>Peter</hi> was first Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Apostles did not <hi>then</hi> attribute to themselves each one his particular <hi>Chair</hi> (understand in that City of <hi>Rome▪</hi> for in other places, others had Chairs besides <hi>St. Peter</hi>) and therefore, says the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,</hi> he is a <hi>Schismatick</hi> who against that one single <hi>Chair</hi> erects another: (understand still in the same place) and this this the Ground and the Authority the <hi>Papists</hi> say the <hi>Pope</hi> has to be Successor to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and to exercise Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over the Universal <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But sure the <hi>Protestants</hi> urge more rationally, in arguing thus: That St. <hi>Peter</hi> wrote <hi>Two Catholick Epistles,</hi> in which he mentions his own departure; and writes to preserve the <hi>Christians</hi> in the <hi>Faith:</hi> but yet in neither of these <hi>Two Epistles</hi> does he commend the <hi>Christians</hi> to the guidance &amp; authority to his pretended <hi>Successor</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Rome;</hi> which sure if St. <hi>Peter</hi> had intended, he would never have forgot to have named it.</p>
            <p>And since the <hi>Papists</hi> so reverence and adore the <hi>Popes</hi> power, let us <hi>Protestants</hi> also admire his way and means of attaining this power: For though the <hi>Papists</hi> say, that as soon as he is made <hi>Pope,</hi> he has his authority immediately from <hi>Christ;</hi> yet at the very same time the <hi>Papists</hi> all know, that he cannot be made <hi>Pope,</hi> but by authority and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the <hi>Cardinals;</hi> so that I am sure by the very same reason, any man that is chosen a Magistrate in any Town under the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Territories, may claim his Authority as immediately received from <hi>Christ,</hi> as well as the <hi>Pope.</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:199118:21"/> And further, that the proving his being made <hi>Pope,</hi> does not render him <hi>infallible,</hi> I could give a hundred instances out of the History of <hi>Popes,</hi> but that will not suit well with my designed brevity, but let's ask the <hi>Papists,</hi> if <hi>Liberius</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> after Two years Banishment, did not by the sollicitation of <hi>Fortunatianus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Aquileia,</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe to <hi>Heresie,</hi> and consequently could not be <hi>infallible.</hi> And though the <hi>Papists</hi> rely so much on the Authority of the Fathers, to support and justifie the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of their <hi>Church;</hi> yet upon true Examination we shall find, they make no more for their Universal Bishop, than St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Two Catholick Epistles</hi> do.</p>
            <p>And for their arguing out of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s 55 <hi>Epistles,</hi> that sure makes rather against, than for them; for there St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> writes to <hi>Cornelius</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but writes not so much to him, as of himself, who was Bishop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> against whom a Faction of <hi>Schismaticks</hi> had set up another Bishop. Now though the <hi>Papists</hi> say reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, <hi>that 'tis a mark of the Ʋniversal Bishop, that other Bishops should make their Addresses unto the Bishop of</hi> Rome; yet sure 'twere better Reasoning to conclude thus: If the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> had been acknowledged Universal Bishop, and his Authority and Supremacy had been believ'd and own'd, sure St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> had not been satisfied with only barely writing him his sad story, (for he did no more,) but doubtless would have made his complaint to him, and desired and expected redress from him, as Universal Bishop over the whole <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> but his not doing so, argued he esteemed him Bishop only of one <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, <hi>St. Cyprian,</hi> all know, did resolutely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose a Decree of the <hi>Roman</hi> Bishop, and all that adhered to him in that one point of <hi>Rebaptizing;</hi> which the Popish Church <hi>at that time,</hi> delivered as a necessary <hi>Tradition,</hi> and Excommunicated the Bishops of <hi>Capadocia, Galatia,</hi> and all that were against <hi>that Tradition,</hi> and would not so much as allow them <hi>lodging</hi> or <hi>entertainment</hi> in <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now since the <hi>Papists</hi> affirm, that not to Rebaptize those, whom <hi>Hereticks</hi> had Baptized, to be a damnable <hi>Heresie;</hi> 'Tis well worth asking the Papists, when this begun to be so? for if they say, from the beginning it was so, then
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:199118:22"/> they must maintain a <hi>contradiction;</hi> for then was St. <hi>Cypria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> a Professor of damnable Heresie; and yet the <hi>Papists</hi> esteem him a Saint and Martyr.</p>
            <p>And on the other side, if 'twere not so from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then did the <hi>Pope</hi> wrongfully Excommunicate thos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Cappadocia</hi> and <hi>Galatia,</hi> without sufficien<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ground of Excommunication and separation, which by thei<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> own Tenents is <hi>Schismatical:</hi> So let them chuse which sid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they please, the <hi>Pope</hi> was in an error.</p>
            <p>And tho <hi>Victor,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> obtruded the <hi>Roma<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Tradition</hi> touching the time of <hi>Easter</hi> upon the <hi>Asian</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, under the pain of Excommunication and Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet we read that <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> and all the other Wester<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bishops, though they did agree with the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> in his Observation of <hi>Easter,</hi> yet they did sharply reprehend his Excommunicating the <hi>Asian</hi> Bishops for their disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him; which most plainly argues, that the Western Bishops thought that not a sufficient ground of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, which the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> did; and therefore i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> must necessarily follow, they did not esteem the <hi>Roman</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop <hi>infallible,</hi> nor the separation from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> an <hi>Heresie.</hi> And this I am sure is true and undeniable reason▪</p>
            <p>The <hi>Popish</hi> Story tells us, That <hi>Optatus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> upbraided the <hi>Donatists</hi> as <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> because they held no Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by adding af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards that they were <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> for they held no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Seven Churches of <hi>Asia;</hi> which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions this Question of the <hi>Papists,</hi> Whether a separation from these seven <hi>Apostolick Churches,</hi> was a mark of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie,</hi> or not? If they say it was not, how comes it that the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Authority is a stronger Argument for the <hi>Popish Church,</hi> than the <hi>Asian</hi> Authority for the <hi>Asian Churches?</hi> And if the <hi>Papists</hi> say, a separation from those seven <hi>Asian Churches,</hi> was a mark of <hi>Heresie,</hi> then they must confess their <hi>Church</hi> was for many years <hi>Heretical,</hi> as separating many years from the <hi>Asian Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Polycrates</hi> Bishop of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> and Metropolitan of <hi>Asia,</hi> despised the <hi>Pope</hi>'s <hi>Ʋniversal Supremacy and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and kept contrary to the Pope, <hi>Easter-day</hi> the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>March.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:199118:22"/>
            <p>And indeed tho the <hi>Papists</hi> do so much quote the <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> yet I find they as little befriend their <hi>Churches Infallibility,</hi> as the <hi>Asian Bishops</hi> themselves have done: for tho the <hi>Papists</hi> say St. <hi>Hierome</hi> conceived it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessary to <hi>conform in matters of Faith,</hi> to the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> yet before the <hi>Papists</hi> brag of that, let them answer us this, <hi>How came it then to pass▪ that St.</hi> Hierome <hi>chose to believe the Epistle to the</hi> Hebrews Canonical <hi>upon the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the</hi> Eastern Church, <hi>and to reject it from the</hi> Canon <hi>of the</hi> Roman Churches <hi>Authority. And how comes it also that he dissented from the</hi> Roman Church <hi>touching the</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non <hi>of the Old Testament?</hi> Let the <hi>Papists</hi> take heed of losing their <hi>Fort,</hi> by endeavouring to maintain their <hi>out-works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to conclude this point, and excuse the <hi>Papists</hi> mistake concerning their <hi>universal Bishop,</hi> we read in <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> of the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> who thought there was none <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eft beside himself in the whole Ringdom of <hi>Israel,</hi> who had not revolted from God; and yet God himself is pleased to assure us he was deceived. And if a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and one of the greatest, err'd in his judgment touching his own time &amp; Country; why may not the <hi>Papists</hi> (subject to the same passions) <hi>err</hi> in their <hi>opinion</hi> and <hi>judgment</hi> about the <hi>Popes</hi> being <hi>Ʋniversal Bishop,</hi> when plain reason tells them, as well as us, that there were other Bishops as much <hi>Ʋniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal</hi> as the <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I now come to examine this <hi>infallible Pope,</hi> whether he cannot make his <hi>infallible Church</hi> more <hi>infallible</hi> than he has made himself; and free the <hi>Popish Church</hi> from <hi>error,</hi> tho he could not the <hi>Pope</hi> from <hi>Heresie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now towards the disproving the pretended <hi>Infallibility</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> I lay this as the foundation of my Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course; That the whole <hi>Roman Church</hi> can be no better than a Cengregation of Men, whereof every particular, not one excepted, and consequently the generality, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a collection of men: and if every one be pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>(as who dare say he is free from sin?)</hi> how can the whole but be defiled with <hi>error?</hi> As reasonably may a man brag he is in perfect health and strength, and yet at the same time confess he hath not one sound part about him. And truly it very much creats my wonder, but does not in the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:199118:23"/> least satisfie my reason, what the <hi>Papists</hi> can pretend by the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of their <hi>Church:</hi> for if they will allow their Pope to be no better than St. <hi>Peter</hi> was, their <hi>Church</hi> to be composed of no better men than the <hi>Holy Apostles</hi> were; I shall desire no more, and I am sure they can never prove so much: for <hi>they that</hi> pretend to it, declare as great an <hi>ignorance,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> did <hi>a sin,</hi> in denying his Lord and Master: and there are many other known circumstances which made St. <hi>Paul</hi> prove him blame-worthy to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> face.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>Apostles</hi> being in error, we have not only the examples of the <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves, who in the time of our <hi>Saviours</hi> Passion, being <hi>scandalized,</hi> lost their Faith in him; and I believe the <hi>Papists</hi> will not say they could lose their <hi>faith</hi> in our blessed <hi>Saviour Christ</hi> without error<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and therefore our Saviour after his Resurrection upbraided them with their Incredulity, and called <hi>Thomas</hi> incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for denying the Resurrection, in the Twentieth o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> St. <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, 'tis most apparent that the very <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves, even after the sending the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> did through Inadvertency, or Prejudice, continue some time in an error, <hi>contrary</hi> to a revealed Truth. And if the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> will not own to know this <hi>Truth,</hi> they may be fully satisfied of it in the Story of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> where they may plainly read, that notwithstanding our <hi>Saviours</hi> express warrant and injunction to the Apostles, <hi>to go and preach to all Nations;</hi> Yet notwithstanding, till <hi>St. Peter</hi> was <hi>better</hi> informed by a Vision from Heaven, and by the Conversion of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> both <hi>St. Peter</hi> and the rest of the <hi>Church,</hi> held it unlawful for them to go and Preach the <hi>Gospel</hi> to any but the <hi>Jews.</hi> Now since we can prove that <hi>St. Peter</hi> did err, and that the <hi>Church</hi> composed partly of the Holy <hi>Apostles</hi> themselves, who were blessed with, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired by the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> could mistake, and that <hi>there is no man free from sin;</hi> and yet that the Body of men that make up the <hi>Popish Church,</hi> should be <hi>infallible,</hi> is, I confess, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side my <hi>faith</hi> to believe, or <hi>reason</hi> to comprehend.</p>
            <p>For sure if the <hi>Roman Church</hi> had been esteem'd by the <hi>Apostles, infallible,</hi> what needed the <hi>Apostles</hi> any other
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:199118:23"/> Creed, than this short Creed; <hi>I believe the Roman Church <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nfallible?</hi> and that would have been more effectual to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eep the Believers of it from <hi>Heresie,</hi> and in the true <hi>Faith,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>han this Apostolical Creed we now have.</p>
            <p>And sure the <hi>Papists</hi> cannot but believe with us, that <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ose Holy Men that wrote the <hi>New Testament,</hi> were not <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nly Good Men, but also Men that were desirous to direct <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s in the plainest and surest way to Heaven. And the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ists</hi> cannot also but believe with us, <hi>that they</hi> were likewise <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>en very sufficiently instructed by the Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he necessary points of the Christian Faith: Therefore cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>inly 'tis most rational to believe, they could not be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>orant of this <hi>unum necessarium,</hi> that all Faith is no Faith, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>cept we believe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was design'd by <hi>God</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o be the <hi>Guide of Faith,</hi> as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> believes, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nd would have us believe so too.</p>
            <p>We also further believe, and that with great reason too, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>at the Writers of the <hi>New Testament</hi> were Wise Men, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ally being they were assisted by the <hi>Spirit of Wisdom;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ch that must know, <hi>that an uncertain Guide was as bad as <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ne at all;</hi> and yet after all this, is it possible for a <hi>Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hical</hi> or <hi>Contemplative</hi> man, nay, for any man that has rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n or common sense, after all these suppositions, to believe <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>at none among these holy Writers of the <hi>New Testament</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ould remember <hi>(ad rei memoriam)</hi> to set down plainly <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>is most necessary Doctrine, not so much as once, That <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e were to believe the <hi>Roman Church infallible?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, that none of the <hi>Evangelists</hi> should so much as <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>nce name this <hi>Popish necessary point of Faith, if they had <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>teem'd it necessary for us to believe it,</hi> when <hi>St. Paul</hi> says, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e kept not back any thing that was profitable for us;</hi> and sure <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Papists</hi> cannot deny, but was is necessary to salvation, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ust be very profitable: And <hi>St. Luke</hi> also plainly tells <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hristians, his intent was <hi>to write all things necessary.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>re it stands also with reason, that when <hi>St. Paul</hi> wrote to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Romans,</hi> he would have congratulated this their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>aordinary priviledge, if he had believ'd it belong'd to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hem.</p>
            <p>And though the <hi>Romans</hi> bring it as a great Argument <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>or them, that <hi>St. Paul</hi> tells them, <hi>Their Faith is spoken al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:199118:24"/> the world over;</hi> Yet pray let them moderate those thought<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> with this consideration, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> said the very same thing to the <hi>Thessalonians:</hi> And let them further consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this, that if the <hi>Roman Faith</hi> had been the <hi>Rule o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Faith</hi> for all the World for ever, as the <hi>Papists</hi> hold; sure St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have forborn to put the <hi>Romans</hi> in fear o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> a possibility, (for though Raillery is much in fashion now<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> sure 'twas not then) that they also, nay the whole <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> if they did not look to their standing might fall into Infidelity, as the <hi>Jews</hi> had done, 1 <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sians</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>And methinks it also stands with great reason, that the <hi>Apostles</hi> writing so often of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>Antichrist</hi> should have given the Christian World this (as <hi>Papists</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) only sure Preservative from them, <hi>To be guided by the infallible Church of</hi> Rome; and not to separate from it upon the pain of damnation.</p>
            <p>Methinks also St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>James,</hi> and St. <hi>Jude,</hi> in their <hi>Catholick Epistles,</hi> would not have forgot giving Christians this <hi>Catholick</hi> Direction of following the <hi>Roman Church;</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> instead of saying, <hi>He that believes that Jesus i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the Christ, is born of God,</hi> might have said, <hi>He that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres to the Doctrine of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, and lives accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, is a good Christian, and by this mark you shall know him.</hi> In a word, can there be any thing more irrational, than to believe, that none of these holy Men, who were so desirous of mens salvation, should so much as once remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to write, that we were to obey the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> but leave it to be collected from uncertain Principles, and by more uncertain Consequences.</p>
            <p>So that upon the whole, I cannot without much wonder look on the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Confidence, and the <hi>Papists</hi> Credulity, in esteeming the <hi>Pope</hi> or his <hi>Councils</hi> to be an <hi>infallible Guide:</hi> sure either they never read what they ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, or else they will not believe what they read, though it be never so known a Truth, and worthy of belief: for if they did, they could never believe the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of the <hi>Popish Church,</hi> For indeed, if they would read the <hi>Popish</hi> Story, or, as I may well call it, the Civil Wars of the <hi>Popes,</hi> you shall find, as I said before, Popes against Popes, Councils
<pb facs="tcp:199118:24"/> against <hi>Councils;</hi> some <hi>Fathers</hi> against others, nay, some against <hi>themselves; new Traditions</hi> brought in, and <hi>old ones</hi> turn'd out; one <hi>Church</hi> against another; nay, the <hi>Church</hi> of one Age against the <hi>Church</hi> of another. In a word, the <hi>Papists</hi> say their <hi>Church</hi> is <hi>infallible;</hi> and all other Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans besides <hi>themselves,</hi> tho more in number than they, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely deny it; and yet we must for all that believe the <hi>Popish Church infallible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to speak the plain <hi>Truth,</hi> and in a word to unravel the real cause of the <hi>Grandure</hi> of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> above all other <hi>Churches,</hi> is only this: <hi>Rome</hi> was the Imperial Town of the Empire, and its greatness was given by Men, and not God; and when afterwards <hi>Constantinople</hi> was the Imperial City, they Decreed that the Church of <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> should have equal Priviledges and Dignities with that of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to end this Discourse, I desire you will please to consider this <hi>Conclusion,</hi> which is, that after all that the <hi>Papists</hi> have said, be it never so much and mighty, <hi>to shew the Infallibility of their Church;</hi> I am verily perswaded they cannot shew more, if so much, out of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> for <hi>their Church,</hi> as the smallest Society of Christians met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in prayer, can for themselves, <hi>that when two or three are met together in my name, I will be amongst them, says the Lord:</hi> And now I have just done this small Discourse, and the Sun is just upon finishing this days visit; I can very readily follow that holy advice of not <hi>letting it go down in my anger:</hi> (which I thank God I have to none living) and therefore am in so much <hi>Charity</hi> with the <hi>Papists,</hi> as to wish that neither <hi>they,</hi> nor <hi>Protestants,</hi> might waist their precious time in meer speculative controversies about words and ceremonies, which of themselves will never carry us to Heaven; but that we may spend our time like wise Christians in the ways and fear of God, which is the only beginning of wisdom; and not consume it in stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying and maintaining of Disputes and Factions; but if we must still differ, let <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Papists</hi> differ in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions but as <hi>Aristotle</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> did, who, tho they were of differing Judgments touching the natures of <hi>Souls,</hi> yet both of them agreed in the main, that all men had <hi>Souls,</hi> and Souls of the same nature.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:199118:25"/>
            <p>And as <hi>Physicians,</hi> though they dispute, whether the <hi>Brain</hi> or the <hi>Heart</hi> be the principal part of a man, yet that all Men have <hi>Brains,</hi> and <hi>Heart,</hi> they sufficiently agree in: So though <hi>Protestants</hi> esteem one part of the <hi>Church-Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> set a higher value on another part, yet the Soul of the <hi>Church</hi> may be in both of them: and though the <hi>Papists</hi> account that a necessary <hi>truth,</hi> which the <hi>Protestants</hi> account neither <hi>necessary,</hi> nor perhaps <hi>ture;</hi> yet in <hi>truth</hi> truly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary they both agree, <hi>viz.</hi> The Apostles <hi>Creed,</hi> and that <hi>Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> are necessary to salvation. And lastly, though <hi>Papists</hi> hold they may be justified by their Works, and <hi>Protestants</hi> hold none can be justified barely by them, (in regard of the Imperfections of their Works) yet on the other side, we so much agree with the <hi>Papists,</hi> as to esteem none can be justified without them: for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repentance, and Charity, none can be good; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both like Health to our Bodies, the want of which is sufficient to disturb all other pleasures. Therefore when we read St. <hi>Pauls Treatise of Justification by Faith without the works of the Law;</hi> let us at the same time read what he writes to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> concerning the absolute necessity of that Excellent Vertue of <hi>Charity,</hi> and they will reconcile one another. And I wish, <hi>that we were all so reconciled in the unity of the Spirit, and in the bond of peace.</hi> And that you, <hi>Madam,</hi> may be the sooner reconcil'd to me, for this tediousness; I shall now make a Conclusion, which after such an overgrown Letter, must needs be the best Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that can be made by,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Errata: <hi>Page</hi> 9. <hi>line</hi> 27. for <hi>past-time,</hi> read <hi>patience.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>The Tryal of <hi>Philip Standsfield,</hi> Son to Sir <hi>James Stans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> of <hi>New-Milns,</hi> for the Murther of his Father. And other Crimes Libell'd againg him, <hi>Feb.</hi> 7. 1688. For which he had Judgment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Historical Relation of several Great and Learned <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists</hi> who did Imbrace the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> with their Reasons for their Change, deliver'd in their own words. 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Seasonable Collection of plain Text of Scripture, for the Use of <hi>English Protestants.</hi> price 2 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>